<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The disorders of love truly expressed in the unfortunate amours of Givry with Mademoiselle de Guise / made English from the French.</title>
            <title>Désordres de l'amour. English</title>
            <author>Villedieu, Madame de, d. 1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35784</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1188</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2145</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12265475</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12265475</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58051</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35784)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58051)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 180:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The disorders of love truly expressed in the unfortunate amours of Givry with Mademoiselle de Guise / made English from the French.</title>
                  <title>Désordres de l'amour. English</title>
                  <author>Villedieu, Madame de, d. 1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 148 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for James Magnes and Richard Bentley ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Desordres de l'amour.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Marie Catherine Hortense Desjardins (known as Mme. de Villedieu). Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [5]-[6].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Givry, Anne d'Anglure, --  seigneur de, ca. 1560-1594.</term>
               <term>Conti, Louise-Marguerite de Lorraine, --  princesse de, 1574-1631.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  16th century --  Fiction.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:58051:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58051:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58051:2"/>
            <p>LICENSED.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 24. 1677.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Roger L'Eſtrange.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58051:2"/>
            <p>THE DISORDERS OF LOVE.</p>
            <p>Truly expreſſed In the unfortunate Amours of <hi>GIVRY</hi> with <hi>MADEMOI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SELLE de Guiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Made <hi>Engliſh</hi> from the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>James Magnes</hi> and <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Bentley,</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden</hi> near the <hi>Piazza</hi>'s, 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:58051:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58051:3"/>
            <head>THE BOOKSELLER TO THE Courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>THE Gentleman that tranſlated this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, for his Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, would not be perſwaded to write a Dedication, nor a Preface to it; and I being unwilling ſo excellent a Piece ſhould go into the world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Commendation, have taken upon me to tell you, that this Book was reckoned
<pb facs="tcp:58051:4"/>in <hi>France</hi> as the beſt piece of that great Wit <hi>M. D. V. D.</hi> and has had the ſame recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion abroad, as in <hi>Holland,</hi> and in other Parts, where it hath been ſeveral times Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. I am very confident it hath lost nothing by the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating, which makes me hope it ſhall have as good Fortune here. I could ſay much in the commendation of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue and Wit of it, but I leave you to find that diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in reading it; which is all that is aimed at by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours</hi> R. Bentley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:58051:4"/>
            <head>Some Books Printed for <hi>James Magnes</hi> and <hi>Richard Bentley.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>PLato</hi>'s Apologie of <hi>Socrates,</hi> or <hi>Phedo,</hi> two Dialogues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the immortality of Man's Soul.</item>
               <item>A Natural Hiſtory of the Paſſions.</item>
               <item>Country Wit.</item>
               <item>Sophonisba.</item>
               <item>Nero.</item>
               <item>Auguſtus Caeſar.</item>
               <item>Abdellazar.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Timothy Taudery.</item>
               <item>Madam Fickle.</item>
               <item>All Miſtaken.</item>
               <item>Engliſh Monſieur.</item>
               <item>Tartuff.</item>
               <item>Andromache.</item>
               <item>Caliſta.</item>
               <item>Forced Marriage.</item>
               <item>The Fool turned Critick.</item>
               <item>Fond Husband.</item>
               <item>Plain-Dealer.</item>
               <item>Moral Eſſays, the ſecond Part.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:58051:5"/>
               <item>Zelinda.</item>
               <item>Count Brion.</item>
               <item>The Happy Slave. <hi>1. and 2.</hi> Parts.</item>
               <item>The Happy Slave. Part. <hi>3.</hi> in the Preſs, which makes the Story compleat.</item>
               <item>The Education of a Prince, in the Preſs.</item>
               <item>The Triumphs of Love over For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, in the Preſs.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>French Novels.</head>
               <item>L'Heureux Eſclave complet, en trois Voll.</item>
               <item>Princeſſe Monferrat.</item>
               <item>Grand Viſiers.</item>
               <item>Galand Eſcroc, ou Comte Brion.</item>
               <item>Memoires de Suede, <hi>3.</hi> Voll.</item>
               <item>The Differences betwixt <hi>Don John</hi> and Cardinal <hi>Nitard,</hi> in French <hi>2.</hi> Voll.</item>
               <item>Mercure Galand, <hi>2.</hi> Voll.</item>
               <item>Le Triomphe de l'Amour ſur la Deſtinèe.</item>
               <item>Le Vice-Roy de Catalogne, in the Preſs.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58051:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> Diſorders of LOVE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE famous <hi>Givry</hi> was deſcended of the Houſe of <hi>Anglure:</hi> And till the Factions that threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the ruine of <hi>France,</hi> divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that Kingdom againſt it ſelf, the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> (who headed the League againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the Third) and the Marqueſs <hi>d'An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glure, Givry</hi>'s Father, were inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Friends: Their Buſineſs, their Deſigns, their Pleaſures were the ſame. Their Children were educated under the ſame Maſters; and though of une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual birth, and deſigned for Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58051:6"/>of different degrees, it was the Dukes pleaſure the Princes his Children ſhould uſe <hi>Givry</hi> as their Brother: <hi>Givry</hi>'s Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was ſo charming that it gain'd him a general affection, and particularly inclined the young Princes to a ready obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their Father's Command. And <hi>Givry</hi> was ſo diſcreet, that the more familiar the Princes were with him, the greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect he paid them, and ſeem'd to have laid the foundation of an inſeparable Union between the Families of <hi>Guiſe</hi> and <hi>Anglure.</hi> But private Friendſhips are ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom proof againſt that violence that breaks aſunder the moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred bonds. The League ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> from the Royal Intereſt, which the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>d' Anglure</hi> reſolved to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to. This ſenſe of duty to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58051:6"/>the King, the Duke look'd upon as an effect of lightneſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude. And the fatal Cloſe of the Aſſembly of the Eſtates at <hi>Blois</hi> having kindled a War in all the Provinces of <hi>France, Givry</hi> became the open and declar'd E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of thoſe perſons, for whom he had once had the higheſt love and eſteem.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> was ſo deeply affected with the agreeable Converſation of the young Princes of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and ſo much admir'd the Charms of the Princeſs their Siſter, that this ſudden change gave him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite trouble. But beſides the favours and hopes the King made uſe of to ſecure his allegiance, the beauty of Madam <hi>Maugiron</hi> was no ſmall attractive to win him to the Court, and fix his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions to be of the Royal Party.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:58051:7"/>
            <p> This Lady was a young Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, though her Husbands Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by a former Marriage would not allow her that quality; and thoſe of their Family deny her a place among their lawful Allian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Count <hi>Maugiron</hi> the Kings Lieutenant of the Province of <hi>Dauphine</hi> having married her for love; and it was pretended they had taken one anothers words without further Ceremony to conſummate the Marriage. But whether the Lady had placed too great a confidence in the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Count, or was decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the impoſture of a perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated Prieſt inſtead of a real one, ſhe had the good fortune by the credit of her Kinſwoman, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de la Noue,</hi> to obtain prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from the King at <hi>Tours,</hi> where ſhe was eſteemed a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Ornament of the Court.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58051:7"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Givry</hi> was much taken with this Lady, nor was ſhe inſenſible of his Charms. He was but one and twenty years old, an age too tender to adventure into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues and myſteries of Love, had not Nature by extraordinary favours exempted <hi>Givry</hi> from the common Rule of things, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him a priviledge above the ordinary rate of men. He had before the age of eighteen per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd the courſe of his Studies, and finiſhed his Exerciſes; was Maſter of the Mathematiques, and all other Learning requiſite to the accompliſhment of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman: He ſpoke Greek, Latine, and all the modern Languages of <hi>Europe,</hi> as well as his Mother Tongue; and in the proceſs of my Story I ſhall have occaſion to obſerve, he was made Captain of the Light-horſe of <hi>France</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:58051:8"/>at two and twenty years of age.</p>
            <p>You may believe a Lover ſo conſiderable, eaſily made a more than ordinary progreſs in his Amour with a Lady, who had for him a violent inclination. She took no longer delight in the ſight of any other: ſhe did open incivilities and affronts to his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals: they ſpent whole days to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in pleaſant diſcourſes and endearing Converſation. And when interrupted by the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his attending the diſcharge of his duty, the lovely Widow writ him Letters ſo kind, that they ſupplyed in a manner the pleaſure of her company.</p>
            <p>Theſe Letters he always carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him, or put them up in a little Box, wherein he kept what he moſt valued. He read them over and over as oft as he had leiſure, and took more care for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58051:8"/>the ſafety of that Box, than for his own life. But at a skirmiſh where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Enemy had the better of thoſe of the Kings Party com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by <hi>Givry,</hi> among the reſt of his Equipage the Box was taken. To know the deep ſenſe he had of this loſs, you muſt be as deeply in love as he was; and, the truth is, he had more than one reaſon to be troubled at it.</p>
            <p>The Children of Count <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giron,</hi> by the former Wife, were in Arms for the League againſt the King, and <hi>Givry</hi> was afraid the Letters might come to their hands, who thinking themſelves concerned to aſperſe the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Mother-in-Law, would be eaſily induced to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the Letters. He was extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly troubled he had expoſed his Miſtreſs to that danger; and had he believed it would have taken
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58051:9"/>effect, he had certainly made ſome raſh attempt for the recovery of the Box. But being as witty as he was amorous, he came to a reſolution to think no more of that accident, when News was brought him that a Trumpet from the Duke of <hi>Mayenne</hi> deſired to ſpeak with him, and brought with him a Box very like his.</p>
            <p>The Box indeed was in truth the very ſame he had loſt; and when the Trumpeter delivered it him, he told him, That the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly League intended not to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age any intrigue of Gallantry: that they had without ſcruple made uſe of ſuch pieces of his Equipage as might be ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for Religion and the Publick Good. But conceiving Love-Letters uſeleſs for advancement of thoſe ends, they had faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſent him back all thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd to him.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58051:9"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Givry</hi> ſmil'd at the irony of the Complement, and having told the Trumpet that the hearts of Heroes were large enough, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain at once the thoughts of love and of War, he diſmiſt him with a preſent, and lock'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf up to peruſe his Letters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; but was extremely ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd to find on a fold of the firſt Letter he look'd upon, Verſes written in an unknown Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, a Copy whereof follows.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Although the tenderneſs of love</l>
               <l>Inſenſibly the ſenſe improve,</l>
               <l>And lovers need a quick and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſenſe,</l>
               <l>To raiſe their love above indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</l>
               <l>Yet oft poor Lovers raviſhing ſweets do prove</l>
               <l>Effects of humour, not of love.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:58051:10"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Givry</hi> very deſirous to know what to apply this Maxim to, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the Letter, which was to this effect.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Madam</hi> de Maugiron's Letter <hi>to</hi> Givry.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>NO,</hi> Givry, <hi>I ſhall never be pleaſed with you, while I find you fully perſwaded I am ſo. You are diligent, faithful, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate: But an entire confidence agrees not with the fineneſs and delicacy of my affection; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect love expects ſo much duty, that he is a ſtranger to it who thinks he has fully performed it. It muſt be your part to render your ſelf a little more capable of fear, it ſhall be my care to revive your courage, and ſettle your confidence. It is not my deſire you ſhould be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of your happineſs, but that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58051:10"/>I ſhould by degrees convince you of it, as I pleaſe; and not find you convinced of it already.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>When <hi>Givry</hi> opened this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he did did it rather of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity to ſee whether the Verſes had been written there by chance, than out of any ſuſpicion they contained a cenſure of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. He lov'd Madam <hi>Maugiron</hi> too well to impute her affection to meer humour or fancy, or to think her humour predominant over her love; but comparing the ſenſe of the Verſes with that of the Letter, he thought it not ſo altogether exempt from being ſubject to blame, as he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly believ'd it. He asked him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf whether it ſavoured not more of humour than love, to declare ones ſelf unſatisfied with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who in the ſame period is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58051:11"/>acknowledged conſtant, diligent, faithful and paſſionately in love? He did not yet give ſentence in favour of the Verſes, but the defence he made for his Miſtreſs againſt them was very weak. And tumbling over the reſt of the Papers in the Box, he found on another Letter theſe Verſes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Think not by long Diſcourſes to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs</l>
               <l>Your paſſions height, or tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</l>
               <l>That love, that grief the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is,</l>
               <l>Which in the heart cloſe Pris'ner lies.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> reproach'd himſelf as guilty of unfaithfulneſs to his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, for paſſing ſo favourable a judgment of theſe Maxims as he did: but notwithſtanding this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58051:11"/>reproaah, he ſearched for more of them, and was glad when he found them. Upon a Letter, where Madam <hi>Maugiron</hi> applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her ſelf for the choice of her love, he found written
<q>
                  <l>Such is love's mighty influence,</l>
                  <l>It ſpoils the judgment, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts the ſenſe;</l>
                  <l>That often we enamour'd are,</l>
                  <l>Indifferently of foul and fair.</l>
                  <l>Happy the man who by that power mov'd,</l>
                  <l>Loves only what is worthy to be lov'd:</l>
                  <l>And is reputed wiſe for loving that</l>
                  <l>Which the ſtrong impulſe of his fate,</l>
                  <l>Not his diſcretion, did incline him to:</l>
                  <l>'Tis not by Choice, but Chance we woe.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:58051:12"/>
            <p> To another Letter, containing many fantaſtical reproaches, there was added,
<q>
                  <l>When the kind fates for Lovers chooſe</l>
                  <l>The hour, each other to enjoy,</l>
                  <l>Who would the pretious minutes looſe,</l>
                  <l>In fruitleſs railing them t'im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy?</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The Verſes on the former Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters had only perſwaded <hi>Givry,</hi> that Madam <hi>Maugiron</hi>'s Letters were liable to cenſure; but theſe laſt carried his reflections a little further: he fancied he had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered a Lady in love, who made her advantages of all the innocent pleaſures of it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced all the myſteries and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues of it under the ſeverity of rules, and exactneſs of Laws.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58051:12"/>And repreſenting to himſelf the good fortune of a man who could affect a heart of that Character, he could hardly forbear envying his happineſs, and permitting himſelf that moment to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that Madam <hi>Maugiron</hi> was not the ſole perſon in the world capable to make him happy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> was then at <hi>Amboiſe,</hi> where part of the Troops under his Command were quartered. The Marqueſs <hi>de Bellegard,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Horſe to the King, in his return from the Army at <hi>Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logne,</hi> paſt through that Town partly to ſee <hi>Givry:</hi> They were intimate friends, and had no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve for each other. <hi>Givry</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him with the adventure of the Box; which they ſent for, that they might view it toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the Marqueſs <hi>de Bellegard</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:58051:13"/>had ſcarce caſt his Eye on the Character of the Verſes, but he thought he knew it, and told his Friend he was very much miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken if it was not the hand of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle de Guiſe.</hi> Of <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> ſays <hi>Givry!</hi> Yes, replies the Maſter of the Horſe, I knew at <hi>Piemont</hi> where I was bred with my Unele, a Daughter of the Baron <hi>de Vins,</hi> whom he married, and to whom <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> writ very often: I have ſeen ſome of thoſe Letters, and dare ſwear the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes you have ſhewed me were written by the ſame hand. <hi>Givry</hi> was a great admirer of <hi>Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle de Guiſe,</hi> when a Child, and eaſily imagin'd what a height of perfection her Charms were by this time arriv'd to. And what ſweeter temptation for a man of one and twenty years of age,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58051:13"/>than to ſee a great and beautiful Princeſs begin to him in Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and encourage him to come on, by advancing firſt towards him. He asked the Marqueſs what he thought of the meaning of thoſe Verſes, whether with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vanity he might not look on them as a favour, and expect a good iſſue? <hi>What good can you expest from them,</hi> anſwer'd the Marqueſs? <hi>a perſon engaged as you are, ſhould rather fear than wiſh for good fortune in this kind; there is nothing more trouble ſome; nor can the pleaſure be great which is deriv'd from a happineſs that reaches not the heart.</hi> 
               <q>Do you think then, <hi>reply'd</hi> Givry, that favourable prevention from <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> cannot reach my heart?</q> 
               <q>I believe you in love with Madam <hi>Maugiron, anſwered the Marqueſs,</hi> and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58051:14"/>were I ſo, another Lady's favour would be but a trouble to me. I own my ſelf in love with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>Maugiron, ſays</hi> Givry, and unwilling to ſacrifice my paſſion to a few Verſes, the deſign whereof I know not: but if <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> intended them as a favour, it is not Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>Maugiron</hi> ſhall hinder me from being ſenſible of it. I am young and ambitious, and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> is one of the moſt beautiful Princeſſes of the world. You would much queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my wit, if having it in my power to be engaged in an intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue of love with her, I ſhould let ſlip the opportunity. I do not ſay the occaſion is offer'd me, for you may be miſtaken in the Character of the Verſes; and though ſhe had writ them, it cannot be doubted but ſhe did
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58051:14"/>it in merriment. But ſuppoſing ſhe intended to make me diſguſt my Miſtreſs, and ſhew me that another might render me more happy, I ſhould be loth to give her the diſpleaſure of finding her ſelf miſtaken. Nor am I of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that becauſe at 21 years old I have had kind thoughts for Madam <hi>Maugiron,</hi> I muſt therefore look upon all other La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies with the Eyes of an Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite.</q> 
               <q>Ah! poor Madam <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giron, ſays the Marqueſs ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> what a condition are you in? if you love <hi>Givry</hi> in earneſt, you are to be pityed.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Though <hi>Givry</hi> thought her not yet in any ſuch danger, yet he fancy'd the Verſes he had read expreſt as much tenderneſs as gallantry, and could readily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> was one of the fineſt Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58051:15"/>in the world. He pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly flatter'd himſelf with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, that ſhe had vouchſafed to correct the Love-Letters that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to him, and had ſent him the amendments under her hand. But all this was dubious; and if it had not been ſo, yet he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from Madam <hi>Maugiron</hi> thoſe marks of tenderneſs, and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of kindneſs, he durſt not once hope for from <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe:</hi> He had not yet reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to quit a real happineſs for a chimerical hope; and therefore returned to Court with Monſieur <hi>de Bellegard,</hi> to ſeek, <hi>ſaid</hi> Givry, in Madam <hi>Maugiron</hi>'s Eyes a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative from the Evils that threaten her.</p>
            <p>They found the King full of joy at News he had lately recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: The King of <hi>Navarre</hi> as he was putting his Army into
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58051:15"/>quarters, met a flying Camp of the Leaguers Army, he fought them and gave them a total rout: many conſiderable Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners were taken, and among the reſt the Baron of <hi>Vins,</hi> whoſe Daughter the Marqueſs <hi>de Belle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</hi> mentioned in his diſcourſe of the Verſes in the Box. This Baron was one of the faithfulleſt Creatures of the Houſe of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and one of the ableſt Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors of the League. The King of <hi>Navarre</hi> ſent him to the King, that he might by good uſage en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to win him to his Party; and he came to Court the very moment that <hi>Bellegard</hi> and <hi>Givry</hi> arrived there. <hi>Givry</hi> was ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moved at the ſight and name of the Priſoner, and was more impatiently deſirous to ſpeak with him, than to ſee Madam <hi>Maugiron;</hi> and aſſoon as he
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58051:16"/>found the opportunity to ſpeak freely to him, <q>Will you not ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect me, <hi>Monſieur le Baron, ſays</hi> Givry, or may I hope that the memory of my infancy will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh me in your affection from the reſt of the Royalliſts? You have diſtinguiſht your ſelf hitherto, by actions ſo miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to our Party, <hi>anſwered</hi> Vins, that I ſhould do you wrong to mix you with the multitude: This is not the way to expreſs a remembrance of that infancy you put me in mind of; and I aſſure my ſelf when the late Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> ſo highly commended your cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and addreſs, he never thought you would one day em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy them againſt the Princes his Children.</q> 
               <q>I am ingag'd to it in duty (<hi>replies</hi> Givry) which the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> would
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58051:16"/>never have adviſed me to be wanting to. I was born a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the King I ſerve, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was of years of diſcretion, care was taken to inſpire me with a blind ſubmiſſion to the Law of Allegiance I owe him. But, Sir, let others leſs ingag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed than you and I judge of theſe things, and tell me, I beſeeeh you, ſome News of the young Princes and Princeſs their Siſter: Do they perform at age, what their infancy promiſed? and is <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> ſo beautiful at eighteen, as ſhe gave us hope for when ſhe was ten or twelve years of Age.</q> The Princes, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Vins,</hi> are worthy Heirs of the bravery and magnificence of their Family: He whom in your time they called the Duke <hi>de Joyeaſe,</hi> who did ſince make his eſcape from the Caſtle of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58051:17"/>
               <hi>Loches,</hi> where he was Priſoner, is wiſe, ſtay'd, and every way fit to bear the title of the eldeſt Son of his Father. The Prince of <hi>Join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> will be one of the handſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Men on Earth: And the young <hi>Chevalier de Guiſe</hi> hath that height of Wit and Courage that add Luſtre to the leaſt of his actions. But the Princeſs their Siſter is infinitely beyond any thing can be ſaid of her, ſhe hath a thouſand Charms proper to her ſelf, not to be found elſewhere, and parts ſo far excelling thoſe of her Sex, that it may be affirmed, the moſt accompliſh't beauty under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is the leaſt of her good qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities. You have ſeen, addes he ſmiling, an Eſſay of her parts, in ſome Verſes that were brought you by the Duke of <hi>Mayenne</hi>'s Trumpeter, which I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded raiſed in you no leſs curioſity
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58051:17"/>than admiration: What, cryes <hi>Givry,</hi> was it <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> made thoſe Verſes? is it poſſible ſhe ſhould take care to play the Critick on my Letters and ſend me them? It was ſhe did it, I aſſure you, and charged me to deliver the Box to you, ſaid the Baron, it fell into the hands of young <hi>Maugiron,</hi> who with great diligence makes his Court to our Princes. He ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them the Letters written to you, not knowing how far he was concern'd in them: And when his Governour knew the Character, and would have para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phras'd upon the intrigue, <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Guiſe</hi> (whom the Princes her Brothers had acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the buſineſs) forbad him, and ſaid, ſhe reſerved too much kindneſs for the memory of your Infancy, to permit a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58051:18"/>Lady you lov'd to be evil ſpoken of. It was generouſly done, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <hi>Givry,</hi> and like a Princeſs of the Houſe of <hi>Guiſe.</hi> But, Sir, have not the Verſes ſomething in them extraordinary? cannot you tell me what induced her to write them? and whether they were made in private, or in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany? I cannot well inform you of that particular, ſaid <hi>Vins,</hi> I was not preſent when the Verſes were made; and when <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Guiſe</hi> ſhewed them me, ſhe told me only, ſhe would let the Court Ladies ſee, that thoſe of the league exceeded them both in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licacy of affection, and in fineneſs of wit. But dear <hi>Givry,</hi> added the Baron, fixing his Eye on him, you have been bred among us, and may go your ſelf to ask the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs what ſhe thought when ſhe wrote them. Do not you bluſh
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58051:18"/>to think you ſhould learn it by a third hand? Or can you imagine the Princes of the holy Union are not able to offer you as good Employments as thoſe you aſpire to with the King of <hi>Navarr?</hi> For 'tis he is the ſoul of your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the Kings name is but the colour you make uſe of to autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize your protecting of Hereſie. I have told you already, reply'd <hi>Givry,</hi> riſing up, we are too far engaged in contrary Parties to expect belief from one another, of what we can ſay to the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the ſeveral Intereſts we have eſpouſed: A Peace, or an abſolute Victory, will unite us better than our diſcourſes: if in the mean time you are permitted to write to the Princes and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> I conjure you to aſſure them, that all the good offices a Man can do in their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58051:19"/>without rendring himſelf unworthy of their eſteem, they may alwayes expect and promiſe themſelves from <hi>Givry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With that he went out, and paſſing to the Kings Lodgings met there the Marqueſs <hi>de Belle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard,</hi> and went with him to take a turn in the <hi>Malle</hi> at <hi>Tours,</hi> where he told his Friend the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe newly had with the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron <hi>de Vins.</hi> 
               <q>I could have ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently aſſured you, ſaid the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs, that theſe Verſes were <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi>'s; and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve I am not much more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in the Judgment I paſt on the Adventure. You will withdraw your love from Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>Maugiron,</hi> and feed your ſelf with fancies about <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Guiſe;</hi> and I know by the air of your Countenance in ſpeaking to me, that part of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58051:19"/>my Prophecy is already fulfilled. But, my dear Friend, yield not at the firſt onſet, rally your Forces if you find them diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; remember that <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Guiſe</hi> is among a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty not ready to be vanquiſh'd: 'tis poſſible you may not ſee her while you live. But could you flatter your ſelf with the hopes of a peace, or ſuch an abſolute victory that might gain you the convenience of ſeeing her, ſhe is the Daughter of an imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Houſe, and will have a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign ſtranger, or a Prince of the Blood to her Husband. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver think ſhe will forego theſe hopes in complaiſance to you; and conſider what a miſerable caſe it is for a Perſon accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the kindeſt endearments of his Miſtreſs, to tire himſelf out with making love to one
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58051:20"/>who only feeds him with fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> had reflected on all theſe particulars before he heard them from his Friend; but by a fate he could not avoid, he mus'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> and ſcarce thought any more of Madam <hi>de Maugiron:</hi> He reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, without the leaſt ſcruple, to conceal from her the recovery of the Box; and no longer thought her Converſation charming as formerly. When ſhe ſpoke kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to him, he remembred the Maxim in Verſe, where <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Guiſe</hi> found fault with expreſſions that are ſtrong, and became clearly of opinion he ſhould have had more love for his Miſtreſs, had ſhe not too much aſſured him of his happineſs: he was diſpleas'd to find it ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly known, and fancied that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58051:20"/>a more private intrigue would have been more pleaſant. And when to all this he added the conceit of being allowed, by a great and beautiful Princeſs, to pretend a right grounded on what had already paſt from her, to entertain her with the diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Love, and perhaps make her forget that Tyranny her high Blood ſeem'd to oblige her to, againſt inferiour Lovers, he gave himſelf up to be intirely poſſeſt with fancies and illuſions he could never get rid of.</p>
            <p>It was long e're Madam <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giron</hi> apprehended the miſchief that threatned her. <hi>Givry</hi> made conſtant viſits to no other Lady, and if at any time ſhe found him melancholy and diſcompoſed, ſhe imputed it to his ambition of Glory and Renown. But the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon being come for opening the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58051:21"/>Campagne; and <hi>Givry</hi> at part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing entertaining his Miſtreſs with no other diſcourſe than of clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Loyre,</hi> and reducing to the obedience of the King all the Towns the League poſſeſt upon that River. <q>Have you no other diſcourſe to entertain me with, <hi>Givry,</hi> ſays ſhe? or can you think me no otherwiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd at your departure, than to be told only what Conqueſts you deſign for the King?</q> He bluſh'd at this reproach, but not being able to confeſs he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it, he excus'd himſelf by telling her, his diſcourſe proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from his earneſt deſire to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der himſelf more worthy of her. <q>'Tis not enough for ſo charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a beauty as yours, ſays he, that your Servant be deeply in Love, but his Love muſt be ſuch you need not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58051:21"/>of, and that his reputation of being a great Captain may countenance and ſupport his pretenſions of Love.</q> 
               <q>Ah, <hi>Givry,</hi> cryes Madam <hi>Maugiron,</hi> it is a noble ambition, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable here: it may afford a Lover ſome comfort againſt troubles abſence produces, but is not a fit ſubject of diſcourſe at parting, if there be true Love in the caſe: the Love you have had for me I ſee is at an end; and whether any diſpleaſure you have taken againſt me, or your immoderate deſire of glory hath poſſeſt your heart, I find my ſelf now wholly excluded it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> was not yet fully aſſured, whether Madam <hi>Maugiron</hi> were in the right: Love at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning appears in diſguiſe, and though his thoughts for <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Guiſe</hi> might well be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58051:22"/>called Love, his mind could not yet yield them that Character. He did all in his power to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade Madam <hi>Maugiron</hi> her ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicions were ill-grounded, and having great power over her, left her ſomewhat better ſatisfi'd.</p>
            <p>Having left Madam <hi>Maugiron,</hi> he went to the Baron <hi>de Vins,</hi> whom by the advice of <hi>Bellegard</hi> he viſited ſeldomer than he could have wiſh'd. The Baron paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately devoted to the ſervice of the Houſe of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> inceſſantly preſt <hi>Givry</hi> to join again with that Family. The Marqueſs <hi>de Bellegard</hi> from whom he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd nothing, obſerving the great progreſs <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> made in <hi>Givry</hi>'s affections, was not a little afraid leſt <hi>Vins</hi> ſhould debauch <hi>Givry</hi> from his allegiance; but not thinking it fit to make the diſcovery of ſo
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58051:22"/>offenſive a doubt, he told him that his frequent enterviews with the Priſoner gave thoſe who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy'd him great advantage againſt him, that he would do well to forbear them. <hi>Givry</hi> had for ſome time follow'd the advice; but being ready to take the Field, and not knowing but an exchange of Priſoners, or ſome fatal blow might deprive him for ever of an opportunity to ſee the Baron a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>again, he reſolved to take leave of him.</p>
            <p>
               <q>I am going, ſays <hi>Givry</hi> ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to the Baron, to add new Crimes to thoſe you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached me with; and if I dye not in the firſt rencounter, there ſhall few Actions paſs this Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne but I will have a ſmall ſhare in them; but I hope this part of my duty may be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the reſt of it; and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58051:23"/>that if upon the general occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I am forced to bear the Character of an Enemy to the League, I may in particular oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences aſſume that of a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servant of the Houſe of <hi>Guiſe.</hi> I know not whether fare will permit you to aſſure them thus much, but if it be in your power I conjure you to do it; and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to tell <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> that the duty which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains me on the Kings ſide is no ſmall Chain upon my affection, that all I do is more liable to complaint than blame; and that if ſhe could read what is written in my heart, ſhe ſhould diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver there more reſpect, and more zeal for her, than the Troops of the League ſhall find contrary appearances in my Actions.</q> Though the Baron had uſed all his endeavours to ſeduce <hi>Givry,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:58051:23"/>and in the firſt tranſports of his affection for the League, was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd with him for being ſo firm to the royal intereſt, he could not forbear eſteeming him the more for it. He embraced him with a great deal of kindneſs, and promiſed to do him all the good Offices he could. <hi>Givry</hi> having thank'd him, took his leave and went to take poſſeſſion of the Charge the King had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, of Camp-maſter Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Light-horſe of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Kings Army made great progreſs this Campagne; the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> in whom the King began to place the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence he ought, had inſpir'd him with a deſire to fight in the head of his Troops, and the two Kings having join'd Forces at <hi>Soulogne,</hi> the place of general Rendezvous, led them along the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58051:24"/>
               <hi>Loire,</hi> where they found not one Town in Rebellion but it ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them. The King took <hi>Gergeau, Gien, La Chaute,</hi> and made himſelf Maſter of all the Bridges above and below <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaus; Piviers, Estampes,</hi> and <hi>Dourdan</hi> had the like fate: And the Kings having paſt the <hi>Seyne</hi> at <hi>Poiſſybridge,</hi> were met there by the Duke <hi>de Montpenſier,</hi> who led their Forces from <hi>Normandy,</hi> and by the Sieur <hi>de Harlay-ſancy,</hi> who had made brave Levies in <hi>Switzerland.</hi> The Kings Army being thus put into the condition he wiſh'd it, for beſieging of <hi>Paris,</hi> he laid Siege to it in <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> 1589.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> in former Sieges had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſignal proof of his Courage and good Conduct. Not a Sally had been made but he bravely repulſed: he had cut of all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58051:24"/>and got the advantage in all Skirmiſhes that hapned; the ſafety of the Army depended on his care. The King of <hi>Navarr</hi> charmed by ſo many brave Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſeeing <hi>Givry</hi>'s Perſon as amiable as his name was illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, honoured him with a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular kindneſs; and till a more conſiderable Government ſhould fall procured him that of <hi>Brie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> was ſcarce in poſſeſſion of it, when he ſurpriz'd ſix thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Buſhels of Corn which they endeavoured to convey into <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> by the help of a counterfeit Paſs. <hi>Givry</hi> caus'd it to be ſeiz'd at <hi>Pont de Samois,</hi> and was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving orders for carrying it to <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beil</hi> where the Kings Magazin was; but having caſt his Eyes on the Man who had the Convoy in charge, he thought he knew him, an Officer of the late Duke <hi>de Guiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:58051:25"/>
            <p> He was not miſtaken. The Man being a principal Officer of the Dukes Houſhold, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Givry.</hi> 
               <q>Is it poſſible, ſays he, that you ſhould hinder the carrying this Corn into <hi>Paris,</hi> and that a Perſon ſo dear to the late Duke my Maſter ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Princeſs his Wife, and the Princeſs his Daughter to the danger of being in want? How in want, ſays <hi>Givry</hi> in great heat, are thoſe Ladies expoſed to ſhare the miſeries of the people? Yes doubtleſs, ſays the Maſter of the Convoy; and the Duke <hi>de Mayenne</hi> to let the beſieged ſee they ſuffer no more than he does, hath made ſo ſmall a reſerve of Corn for himſelf, that all his Houſe, and particularly that of Madam <hi>de Guiſe,</hi> was upon the point of being in want when I left
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58051:25"/>them.</q> 
               <q>They ſhall not want it, reply's <hi>Givry;</hi> and you may aſſure Madam and <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> that they ſhall never receive from me any Perſonal diſpleaſure.</q> With that, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting only his growing paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he made him a good Paſs, and gave him a Guard to bring him without danger to the firſt Retrenchments.</p>
            <p>This Action was too publick not to be diſcovered: The King was informed of it. And thoſe who envy'd the merit of <hi>Givry</hi> repreſented it as much to his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage as poſſible: it was really of great importance. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the reducing or reſiſtance of <hi>Paris</hi> depended abſolutely the Peace, or the War: That Town was the ſeat and ſupport of the Rebellion. To take <hi>Paris</hi> from the League, was to blow up the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58051:26"/>very Foundations of the League; and to ſend in thither the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment could not but appear a Crime highly puniſhable. And ſome Priſoners taken at a Sally informed, that if that Convoy had been ſtaid one day longer, the Citizens were reſolved to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen their Gates; that it was not in the Duke of <hi>Mayenne</hi>'s power to keep them longer from doing it; and that nothing but the ſight of that Corn, and promiſes of more to be brought in the ſame way, could have appeaſed the people. This Circumſtance ſo highly aggravated <hi>Givry</hi>'s fault, that the King was in extreme wrath againſt him, which the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of all his Friends could not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe; ſo that the King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varr</hi> was forced to ſend for him to come in Perſon to juſtifie himſelf. His excuſe had been excellent, had
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58051:26"/>he been to clear himſelf before the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> from whom all faults of Love had their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of courſe. But beſides that the King was not of that temper, <hi>Givry</hi> could not reſolve to lay open his folly, and made ſo piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a defence, that his beſt Friends and Protectors were ready to condemn him. The King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre</hi> ſent him word of it, and having told him from the King, That he muſt juſtifie himſelf bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or ſtand convicted of Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence with the Enemy; he let him know there was no mean to be found betwixt theſe extremes; ſo that <hi>Givry</hi> was forced to make the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> a clear con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the ſecret motive of his Fault.</p>
            <p>This Prince who feared to find <hi>Givry</hi> more criminal, was mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſed with the Relation, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58051:27"/>running to inform the King of the truth, perſwaded him the fault was pardonable in a young Man, and that in caſe he could be more circumſpect for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, this firſt fault deſerved on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a reprimand. The King gave him a very ſevere one, and it was the laſt from the Mouth of that poor Prince, who was traiterouſly aſſaſſainated on the morrow. On this lamentable occaſion <hi>Givry</hi> expreſt his real ackowledgements of thoſe markes of eſteem he had received from the King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre:</hi> He was the firſt that ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him <hi>King of France,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the Marqueſs <hi>de Bellegard,</hi> and ſeveral others, to do the like; and expreſt ſo much conſtancy and reſolution againſt thoſe who would not joyn with him, that it may be truly affirm'd, the new King received from him the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58051:27"/>and tranquillity of the beginning of his Reign. Not but that the Crown did of right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to him, but that the Law had declared him incapable, upon the account of his Religion. There was then ſo great a Force in arms againſt him, that had certainly taken the Crown from him, if thoſe foreign oppoſitions had been ſeconded by any domeſtick diſorders. <hi>Givry</hi> alone appeaſed the Seditious and encouraged the Fearful. The new King being ſenſible of it, thank'd him in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions ſo tender and kind, that the Court look'd upon <hi>Givry</hi> as a declared Favourite.</p>
            <p>The firſt troubles occaſion'd by the change, being ſomewhat ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed, the King took his Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters at <hi>Meudon,</hi> where he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Deputies of his <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and Uuniverſity of <hi>Paris,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:58051:28"/>who conjured him to render his Religion conſiſtent with his Rights. A Conference was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to be held for that purpoſe; and that things might be debated with the greater freedom, he granted a Ceſtation of Arms for fifteen dayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> received the news from the King's mouth, as he came out of the Council; the King ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſmiling, That, during the Truce, he might go and receive thanks for the ſuccours he had ſent <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe:</hi> This was licence enough for a young Man of his Curioſity; a curioſity that well might be called a paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Love.</p>
            <p>He went from <hi>Meudon</hi> the ſame inſtant with his Friend <hi>Rellegard,</hi> who would not let him go alone, and mingling themſelves with the Guard appointed the Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58051:28"/>they were received together with them into the Town. They went immediately to the <hi>Hoſtel de Guiſe,</hi> to diſcover where the young Princeſs uſually walked, that they might ſee her without being taken notice of. They were told ſhe was at the <hi>Tuilleries,</hi> with the reſt of the Princeſſes of of the Family, to know the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of the Deputies journey, who were to have Audience there.</p>
            <p>The two Adventurers got thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and were ſo fortunate to learn from the firſt Livery-men they asked, That <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> being apparently too young to enter into deliberations of State, was walking alone in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: Thither they went, and had not walked thirthy paces, but they perceived her coming to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them; they drew off at ſome diſtance, that they might
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58051:29"/>look upon her with more liberty. <hi>Givry</hi> thought her then a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more charming than the Baron <hi>de Vins</hi> had deſcribed her. The Marqueſs <hi>de Bellegarde</hi> had never ſeen her before. He had met his Uncle at the Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Marquiſate of <hi>Saluces,</hi> follow'd him to his death, and came not to Court till after the death of the late Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> who had removed all his Family thence. He was ſurpris'd at the Beauty and Majeſty of this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and confeſſed that Madam <hi>de Maugiron</hi> was not to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> was but too much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the ſame opinion; the ſight of the Princeſs had now perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, what the Verſes and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions of <hi>Vins</hi> had but begun. <hi>Givry</hi> was ſeiz'd with a ſtrange heat of affection: he look'd on
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58051:29"/>Princeſs with ſo much attention that he could not hear Monſieur <hi>Bellegarde.</hi> And both advancing to ſee her at a nearer diſtance, they were obſerved, and gave her the curioſity to enquire who they were that appeared ſo handſom and of ſo haughty a meen. She ſent a Gentleman to ask them if they came to engage in a Party? and whether they wanted one to preſent them to the General, the Duke of <hi>Mayenne</hi> her Uncle?</p>
            <p>
               <q>We are not now to engage in a Party for the War, <hi>Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle,</hi> (ſayes <hi>Givry</hi> approaching her) but ſhould eſteem our ſelves happy, if protection were offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us to engage here in a Party of Love: Whatever we ſee at <hi>Paris</hi> invites us to ſuch an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement: The Ladies here are admirable, and the Conjuncture of the Siege furniſhes frequent
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58051:30"/>occaſions to do them ſervice: But there are ſo many Competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors ambitious of this Honour, that as for me I fear I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken too late, and am not likely to find any place void.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> knew <hi>Givry</hi> as ſoon as he ſpoke, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved for her diverſion, to uſe him as an Adventurer unknown. <q>Thoſe of your Age <hi>(ſays ſhe)</hi> are ſeldom expoſed to want of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment: they engage and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engage with ſo much eaſe, that Love never fails to find them buſineſs: at the worſt they may liſt themſelves Volunteers, which is not the worſt Employment in the Militia of Love. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of a Volunteer hath not buſineſs enough for a Soul like mine, <hi>Mademoiſelle,</hi> (reply'd <hi>Givry</hi>) I have more experience than my age promiſeth, and I
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58051:30"/>muſt take it as an injury, if Love allow me not a place among his tryed Souldiers. The experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence you may have gain'd elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, ſays <hi>Mademoiſelle,</hi> will perhaps not be valued among the Ladies of the League: they poſſibly may be afraid the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Love are altered among you, as thoſe of Religion; and that being accuſtomed to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Party of Hereſie, they may not find in you a Faith ſo pure as they expect in their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Marqueſs <hi>de Bellegarde</hi> had hitherto been ſilent, having given his Friend the honour of ſpeaking firſt. But hearing the Lovers of the Royal Party taxed of Hereſie, he thought himſelf obliged to defend them. <q>We are very willing to make proof of our faithfulneſs againſt the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58051:31"/>Lovers of the League, <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle,</hi> ſaid he; and this kind of Combat would be more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous for us than Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats of War: it being more eaſie to be perfectly in Love with the Ladies of the League, than to conquer the Princes of that Party.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As Monſieur <hi>de Bellegarde</hi> was ſaying that word, Madam <hi>de Guiſe</hi> came to them; and with her, Madam <hi>de Nemours,</hi> her Mother in-Law, Madam the Dutcheſs of <hi>Mayenne,</hi> the Lady <hi>Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſſe Villars,</hi> her Daughter by a former Husband; Madam <hi>d'Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male,</hi> formerly <hi>Mademoiſelle d'El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoeuf,</hi> and ſeveral other Ladies, who came from the Audience of the Deputies to take the Air in the Garden.</p>
            <p>They all knew <hi>Givry,</hi> and Madam <hi>de Guiſe</hi> having the Story of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58051:31"/>Convoy, and <hi>Givry's</hi> Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment freſh in her memory, ran to him with open Arms, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced him, as if he had been then (as formerly he was) her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Companion in the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of their Youth. She beck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to <hi>Mademoiſelle,</hi> her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to do the like; and the young Princeſs not expecting a ſecond Command, <q>Think not, (ſaid ſhe ſaluting him,) that I knew you not till my Mothers arrival, you were not ſo much out of my memory: But, adds ſhe, leaning towards his Ear, you ſerve a Miſtreſs ſo delicate, that I held my ſelf obliged to be cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> could not anſwer theſe obliging expreſſions, being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by the Queſtions and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſes of the other Ladies. One ask'd him if he came to render
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58051:32"/>himſelf up to his old Friends, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother reproached him for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving forſaken them. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd his Anſwer in deep Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences made to them, or in am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous terms; and letting them know that his Friend there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent was the Marqueſs <hi>de Belle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde,</hi> Maſter of the Horſe to the King, they acquainted the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies that their Viſit was a Fruit of the Truce; and that it ſhould not be their fault, if they ſhould not be allowed by a good Peace to wait on them oftner.</p>
            <p>Theſe Diſcourſes held till Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet. <hi>Givry</hi> had a deſire to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue them longer, and to lye that night at <hi>Paris:</hi> but <hi>Bellegarde,</hi> though charm'd with the ſight and Converſation of <hi>Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle de Guiſe,</hi> thought it not fit to hazard ſo long a ſtay, without particular leave from his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:58051:32"/>He drew his Friend as it were from the Garden, where he ſtaid above an hour after the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies were gone; and taking the way to the Kings Quarters, they had no other Diſcourſe as they went, but of the Beauty and Charms of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe. Givry</hi> had till this time obſerved ſome meaſure of civility towards Madam <hi>de Maugiron:</hi> He was ſenſible he loved her not as he had formerly done; yet he made ſome ſcruple of betraying the hopes of a Lady in Love with him, who never gave him any cauſe of complaint: She ſtaid at <hi>Chinon</hi> with Queen <hi>Louiſe,</hi> and writ to <hi>Givry</hi> by every Courier; and he as punctually anſwered her Letters. He had gain'd her the protection of the new King, and loved her ſtill as an obliging acquaintance; but with ſo much
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58051:33"/>indifference, the Love he retained for her could not diſturb the peace of his ſpirits. Yet the ſight of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> had utterly deſtroy'd thoſe ſmall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of Kindneſs for Madam <hi>de Maugiron.</hi> At his return from <hi>Paris</hi> he found at his Quarters a Letter from Madam <hi>Maugiron,</hi> and forgot to read it; two or three more had the ſame fortune. <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> had ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely poſſeſt both his affection and fancy. <q>What Charms ſhe has! ſays he to the Marqueſs <hi>de Belleogarde,</hi> what a mixture of Majeſty and ſweetneſs appears in her? How quick, yet how pleaſing and agreeable ſhe is! Did you ever ſee a Phyſiogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſo witty, and ſo open and clear as hers is? Her Eyes have a Luſtre ours can hardly endure to behold it. Smiles ſeem to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58051:33"/>dwell on her Lips; and what can be more delicate and eaſie, than her Converſation?</q> 
               <q>She is, I fear, anſwers <hi>Bellegarde,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way too perfect for your repoſe; and your Friends could have wiſhed the Baron of <hi>Vins</hi> had not drawn her Picture ſo much to the Life.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> ſtirr'd not out of his Quarters the night he return'd from <hi>Paris.</hi> His ſpirits were in diſorder, and his affections in too great a heat to be adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured into the company of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons unconcern'd; and one nights reflection was little enough to put him into a condition to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at Court. The King no ſooner ſaw him but he took him aſide, and with the familiarity which gain'd him ſo many hearts; <q>Well, <hi>Givry,</hi> ſays he, have you ſeen <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58051:34"/>do you find her worthy of what ſhe made you do againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of your Party?</q> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> Sir, replyes <hi>Grvry,</hi> is a Perſon of ſo admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perfections, that your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſhall permit me, if you pleaſe, to forbear the deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I know your heart ſuſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible of amorous impreſſions; and mine is ſo inflamed, I ſhould certainly dye, ſhould any acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent croſs my deſire.</q> 
               <q>Fear no ſuch accident from me, ſays the King; you are more than one way ſufficiently Guarded on that ſide. I have kindneſs for you, and underſtand very well what Love can do in a Man of your temper. As for me, I am ſo prepoſſeſt with another Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</q> that all other Beauties in the World cannot reach my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. With that, as a new
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58051:34"/>evidence of his favour, he truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with the ſecret of his paſſion for <hi>Gabrielle d'Eſtree,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards Dutcheſs of <hi>Beaufort.</hi> This Amour of the Kings was then in its firſt heat, and he ſpoke of his Miſtreſs to <hi>Givry</hi> with ſuch tranſport, that <hi>Givry</hi> could no longer ſuſpect danger on that ſide; but made the King a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful relation of all the paſſages at <hi>Paris:</hi> To which he added an humble Petition, that the King would allow him the liberty to make his advantage of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences of the Truce. The King left him abſolute Maſter of his actions, ſo that he went back the ſame day to <hi>Paris,</hi> where <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> expreſt a deſire to ſee the Kings Camp; which they agreed ſhould be done on the morrow. <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> came in company of the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:58051:35"/>Princeſs her Mother; and <hi>Givry,</hi> having received them at the foot of the Retrenchments, conducted them under certain Tents adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Flowers, and with Greens. He treated them there at a magnificent Collation, ſerved in by Boys in the habits of Slaves: The Collation being over, <hi>Givry</hi> brought the Ladies to a little Plain, where, with the Kings leave, he had cauſed ſome Troops to be drawn up in Battalia, and Exerciſed them before the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. The Princeſſes were very much delighted with the ſight, and in their return to <hi>Paris</hi> were attended by a Company of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Trumpeters, who made an excellent Conſort of Military Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and led them as triumphant to the Walls of the City.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs <hi>de Bellegarde,</hi> who, under pretence of ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58051:35"/>the intentions of his Friend, was glad of the occaſion to make his Court to <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> entertain'd the Ladies of the League with a falſe attack of a Fort.</p>
            <p>The King was not diſpleas'd at theſe Entertainments, in hopes they might conduce to ſweetning and mollifying the ſpirits exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, and improve the Truce in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a laſting Peace: But theſe hopes ſoon vaniſh'd, for the Duke of <hi>Mayenne</hi> had propoſed the Truce for no other end, than to give the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> (who had promiſed him aid) the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience of advancing to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of <hi>Paris;</hi> and as ſoon as he knew the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> was on his March, he briskly broke off all further Conference, and the War became more obſtinate than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:58051:36"/>
            <p> The King was extremely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed at this Juggle, and <hi>Givry</hi> was no leſs afflicted. He had diſcourſed ſeveral times, to his great ſatisfaction, with <hi>Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle de Guiſe,</hi> but had not decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to her his paſſion. He had the ſenſe to think more time and more ſervices neceſſary, to make way for ſo high an attempt; but conceived he had obſerved in the young Princeſs, that freedom of ſpirit that gave cauſe to believe ſhe would be more taken with beight of merit, ſupported with exceſs of affection, than with height of birth void of qualities ſuitable: They had often ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of Madam <hi>Maugiron; Giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> aſſured the young Princeſs, that the Verſes ſhe had ſent him, had diſſipated thoſe miſts of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection that blinded him; and that ever ſince, he look'd on that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:58051:36"/>Lady with a great deal of indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> took pleaſure in making him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat this proteſtation; and the day before the Conferrences were broken of, ſhe carryed on this diſcourſe ſo far, as to tell <hi>Givry</hi> he deſerved better Fortune, than to be the Knight-Errant of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Dame. Had he deſired her to explain her ſelf, 'tis poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he had found ſhe ſpoke this at random. But he was ſo willing to be deceived, that he found matter in her general and ambiguous expreſſions, to flatter himſelf into hopes his reaſon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared groundleſs; however he thought he could never be angry enough with the Duke of <hi>may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enne,</hi> for hindring him to clear his doubts, by ſo ſudden and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected a Rupture.</p>
            <p>He hop'd to have done it at
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58051:37"/>parting with the Princeſs, and ran towards <hi>Paris</hi> to take his leave of her, but found all further Communication already prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Proclamation, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd much troubled to the Kings Quarters; and after a few days marched away with the King to meet the Duke of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</hi> This March ſet <hi>Paris</hi> at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and no leſs troubled than angred the Royaliſts, thus forced to raiſe the Siege: But there was no remedy, and it was of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to fight the Enemy before he ſhould have taken his advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: the King advanced for that purpoſe to <hi>Cheles,</hi> where the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies lay ſix dayes in ſight of each other, and the Kings not able to force the other to fight. The Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> was made believe that the Kings Troops were but few, and not in good order:
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58051:37"/>but when the Duke had from a little Hill taken a view of them in Battalia, he found himſelf not in a condition to hazard a Battel; and drawing off in a thick Fog that roſe one of thoſe mornings, he contented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with ſurprizing <hi>Lagny,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a League of his Camp. The King did what he could to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour the Town; but the deſign of taking it was ſo cloſely laid, that his Majeſty perceived it not until it was too late to prevent it.</p>
            <p>This exploit of the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> having aſſured to the <hi>Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fians</hi> the freedome of the River <hi>Marne,</hi> ſet their City at full li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from the inconveniences of the Siege: but this relief came ſo late, it did them little good. The bodies of the Citizens had been ſo dried up in the Dearth,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58051:38"/>that they could not bear a plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful feed: The change of Food be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came as mortal as the Famine at <hi>Paris;</hi> and the Kings Army was now as neceſſitous as the Leagues had been. The taking of <hi>Lagny</hi> had block'd up the River <hi>Marne,</hi> the Garriſons of the League in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Towns in the heart of <hi>France</hi> intercepted his Convoys; and during the Siege of <hi>Paris,</hi> the Country about it was laid ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate it had neither Corn nor Forrage: This forced the King to ſend the greateſt part of his Souldiers to refreſh themſelves at their reſpective homes. The Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> having had the glory of ſetting <hi>Paris</hi> at liberty, was willing to ſecure it by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieging <hi>Gorbeil:</hi> The Town held out a month, and was not taken but by a General aſſault.</p>
            <p>The brave <hi>Givry</hi> ſtill deeply
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58051:38"/>reſenting the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi>'s arrival, which broke off the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and removed the hopes of Peace, could not with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſee him enjoy that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. He got together the Garriſons of his Government of <hi>Brie,</hi> andegg'd on by a courage which ſeem'd more than Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, retook in one night by <hi>Scala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> a Town before which one of the greateſt Captains of his time laid Siege a whole Month.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> had ſo little foreſight of this Action, that part of his baggage was at <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beil</hi> when retaken; and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly many rare Eſſences, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome were neceſſary for his health, and others excellent for delicate ſmells. <hi>Givry</hi> ſent them all to <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> to diſpoſe of at her pleaſure, and ſent her word by the Gentleman
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58051:39"/>who had the Paſs-port for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying them, That he eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf ſo happy, in having been once able to give paſſage to the Corn deſign'd for her ſervice, that he was extremely deſirous to improve that advantage; that the Convoys ſhe ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in ſhould no more be ſtaid at <hi>Corbeil</hi> than they had been at <hi>Pont Samois,</hi> but that he was too jealous of the opportunities of doing her ſervice, to permit that this liberty ſhould depend upon the Duke of <hi>Parma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Complement was civil, and the freedome <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> uſed towards <hi>Givry</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Truce, might have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged him to ſome higher piece of Gallantry. But the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer ſhe gave <hi>Givry</hi>'s Meſſenger was, That ſhe would receive nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Meſſage nor Preſent from
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:58051:39"/>his Maſter; that he ſhould carry him back the Eſſences he had ſent, and tell him, the familiarity ſhe had vouchſafed to uſe towards him hindred, her not to be <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> nor him from being, as he was, <hi>Givry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was ſo much ſurpriz'd at this Anſwer, that he made the Gentleman repeat what he had ſaid to her; and finding nothing in his expreſſions that might oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion a return of ſo much ſcorn and contempt, would have put all at ſtake to know the meaning. But the King gave him no leiſure for it, having commanded him to attend him preſently with his Forces, to fall upon the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> in his retreat for <hi>Flanders.</hi> The King gaul'd him in his March, and having purſued him as far as the Tree of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> came to refreſh himſelf at St. <hi>Quentin.</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:58051:40"/>There he received News that the Marqueſs <hi>d'Humieres</hi> had taken <hi>Corby</hi> from the League. The King expreſt his ſatisfaction at this News by publick rejoicings, wherein he was pleaſed the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies at St. <hi>Quentin,</hi> and the Parts thereabouts, ſhould have their ſhare. He ordered ſeveral diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements to be given them, and expected that <hi>Givry</hi> who was no leſs gallant than brave, ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his cuſtome, bear a principal part there; but he was ſo fretted and vex'd at the uſage he had received from <hi>Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle de Guiſe,</hi> that occaſions of joy became a very torment to him.</p>
            <p>He begg'd the King's leave to return to his Government, where he uſed many endeavours to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe the wrath of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe;</hi> and to diſcover the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:58051:40"/>cauſe of it. He made inroads to the very Gates of <hi>Paris,</hi> took ſeveral Priſoners, and ſending them to the Princeſs, acquainted her by them, that he would not ſubmit to the prohibitions he had received, till ſhe would make known to him by what Crime he had occaſioned them. But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the evidences he could give her of reſpect and zeal, ſhe perſiſted in a ſcornful ſilence; or if at any time ſhe broke it, it was to return him harſher An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers than thoſe his Gentleman had brought him. He paſt a whole Winter in this grievous condition; and to increaſe his vexſation and ſorrow, every day produced new reproaches from Madam <hi>Maugiron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She call'd him perjured, light, inconſtant, ingrate; and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a thouſand extravagances he
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58051:41"/>thought himſelf obliged, in civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, to prevent. He had for ſome time neglected anſwering her Letters, in hopes by this means to diſcourage her from writing: But finding to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that this did but make her more prolix and impetuous in her ſtile, he ſent her word plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he had no more love for her, that he was ſorry for't, and wiſh'd he could have lov'd her all his Life; but that Man is not Maſter of his affections; and he pray'd her to forget an ungrateful Perſon unworthy to poſſeſs a place in her thoughts. This terrible Letter was ſo far from wakening her anger, and effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her cure by a generous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, that it produced only ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn proteſtations of an unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable Conſtancy.</p>
            <p>There needs but an ordinary
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:58051:41"/>Love, writes ſhe to him, to make us love him that loves us. My Affection being a great deal more perfect, can produce greater ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects; and I will love you ſcornful and ingrate, as I lov'd you when I thought you faithful and kind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> had the honeſty to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach himſelf for the ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude he was forced to, and would have given all he was worth to ſee Madam <hi>Maugirons</hi> affection cool to an indifference. But when he reflected on the rigors of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> it height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his ſenſe of them, and the right he conceived he had to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the ſtrangeneſs of his Fortune.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the ſeaſon was come for taking the Field, and the hopes of Peace appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every day more remore; the King deſign'd to beſiege <hi>Roan,</hi> as
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:58051:42"/>a place whoſe ſituation and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance appeared of moment towards the reduction of <hi>Paris.</hi> This Siege is mentioned in Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as one of the hotteſt during theſe Wars. Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of <hi>England</hi> had ſent the King a powerful Fleet, which blocked up the City toward the Sea: His Majeſties Troops, which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in Perſon, begirt it on the Land ſide: And the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>Villars,</hi> Son-in-Law to the Dutcheſs of <hi>Mayenne,</hi> defended it. He poſſeſt himſelf of the Fort St. <hi>Katherine,</hi> where he had Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries which fired continually. The beſieged made furious Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and ſcarce a day paſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Skirmiſhes which deſerved the name of bloody Fights. In one of theſe <hi>Givry</hi> was dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly wounded in the Shoulder; and the ſorrow he lay under on
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58051:42"/>the account of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> increaſing the dang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> his Wound, the Chyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thought him at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> death. The King had a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> affection for this young Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> doubted whether he had in his Army a Perſon capable to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his place; and declared this doubt ſo publickly, that many were diſpleas'd at it: but he ſlighted their murmurs, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing informed of ſome expreſſions <hi>Givry</hi> had let fall, that he hated his Life, and was glad to ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in danger to loſe it; his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty went to the Village they had carried him to, and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conjured him to tell him what caſt him into this deſpair.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> was too much charmed with the goodneſs of his Maſter, to hide from him a ſecret he had expreſt ſo great a curioſity to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58051:43"/>know: He told him what had hapned at <hi>Corbeil,</hi> and the relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on having ſo diſturb'd him, that he thought his life at an end: <q>I perceive, ſays he, I ſhall dye without knowing the cauſe of my misfortune. I confeſs I might look on my raſhneſs as cauſe ſufficient, but having ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver declared it but by my looks, which <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> hath no reaſon to pretend ſhe underſtood, I cannot fancy it is ſhe hath caſt me into this cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. I beſeech your Majeſty, by that goodneſs whereof I have received ſo many eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and which makes you bear ſo tender a part in the extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gances of an unfortunate Lover, that you will cauſe a requeſt to be made to <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> when I am dead, not to abhor my memory as ſhe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:58051:43"/>to do my Perſon; but to believe this Petition had not come ſo late, could I have juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly roproach'd my ſelf with the leaſt deſire might juſtly offend her.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The King was ſo affected with <hi>Givry</hi>'s diſcourſe, that he could not forbear letting fall ſome tears. He pray'd him to do all in his power to help the Chyrurgeons in the Cure; and having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to him a deſign, he thought proper to give him ſome comfort; as ſoon as he left him he put it in execution.</p>
            <p>The Chevalier <hi>d'Oiſe,</hi> Brother to the Marqueſs <hi>Villars,</hi> had been taken Priſoner at a Sally; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing allyed to an Uncle of <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> was very well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with her: the King gave him his liberty, on conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he ſhould know of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58051:44"/>wherein <hi>Givry</hi> had diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her, and ſhould give him an account of it.</p>
            <p>The Priſoner acquitted himſelf faithfully of his Charge, and haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to <hi>Paris,</hi> did as haſtily inform his Majeſty, that <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> complained of a Letter which <hi>Givry</hi> had written, and diſcourſed in it of Love to her; that ſhe was highly offended at the liberty he had taken, and would have puniſhed him with immortal ſcorn, but that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's generoſity to the Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier <hi>d'Oiſe</hi> merited her gratitude and thankful acknowledgments, which moved her to promiſe his Majeſty ſhe would forget this fault of <hi>Givry</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>This promiſe gave him a little comfort, but withall troubled him with new doubts and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities. He had not written to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:58051:44"/>
               <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> and could not imagine who had forged the Letter. He knew not whether he was to grieve or rejoice, that his ſecret was thus revealed; but all things conſidered, as it is of greater advantage for a Lover to be known ſuch, than to burn un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perceived; he took heart again, and recovered his courage by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, which added to his good temper, quickly diſſipated the fears conceived of his Life.</p>
            <p>His Life became every day more neceſſary for the Progreſs of the King's Arms, which his ſickneſs had viſibly retarded. The Officers of the Cavalry, who had an intire confidence in the Bravery of <hi>Givry,</hi> who had gain'd their hearts by his civility and kindneſs, did that under his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct they did not under any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Ever ſince his hurt they
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:58051:45"/>were always defeated; the King durſt not put them on any vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Enterprize under any other Chief. And the Duke of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> coming the ſecond time in aid of the Leaguers, forced his Majeſty to raiſe his Siege from before <hi>Roan,</hi> as he had forced him to raiſe that from before <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <head>The Second Part.</head>
            <p>THE King uſed his utmoſt endeavours to repair the diſadvantages the Duke of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma's</hi> firſt Expedition had put him to: he advanced to encounter him by the way; he long kept the Duke of <hi>Mayenne</hi> (who had taken the Field) from joining him. And when at length they were joined, he inveſted them at
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:58051:45"/>
               <hi>Yvetot,</hi> and at <hi>Caudebec;</hi> and had there finiſhed the War, had not ſome of his Generals preferr'd their particular intereſts before the publick tranquility. The Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> was dangerouſly wounded at <hi>Caudebec,</hi> and in few months after dyed of that wound. The death of ſo formidable an Enemy made the King ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends for the miſcarriage of his Enterprize againſt <hi>Roan.</hi> He ſent his Army into Winter Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and taking his own at <hi>Giſors,</hi> ſent for the fair <hi>Gabrielle,</hi> for whom his Paſſion was now grown ſo violent, he could no longer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> had not been at any of theſe Expeditions, having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued at his Government of <hi>Brie,</hi> where he endeavoured to put himſelf in a condition to clear the Myſteries of his Adventure. The
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:58051:46"/>more he thought upon it, the more perplex'd it appeared. In the midſt of theſe reflections, when he began to look abroad, with deſign to take the Field, as he was entring <hi>Melun,</hi> they brought him a Gentleman be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Madam <hi>de Guiſe,</hi> who conjur'd him by that Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger to grant her a Paſs to go viſit the Dutcheſs, her Mother-in-Law, who was fallen ſick at <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours</hi> in her return from <hi>Bourhon,</hi> where ſhe had been taking the Waters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> ſtaid not for the Kings leave to ſatisfie her requeſt, but preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming on his Maſters goodneſs, and confidently undertaking for it, he ſent Madam <hi>de Guiſe</hi> a Paſs-port as large and effectual as ſhe could wiſh; and went to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive her at the entry of his Government, and Conucted her
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:58051:46"/>to <hi>Melun,</hi> where ſhe lodged one night. <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied her Mother this Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; and as ſoon as <hi>Givry</hi> had a ſight of her, he endeavoured to gather from her looks his good, or bad fortune; but diſcovered only a civility ſo very indifferent, he could not ground any judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon it.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>de Guiſe</hi> that even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſpatch'd a Courrier to <hi>Nemours,</hi> to inform the old Dutcheſs of the hour ſhe thought to arrive there. And while ſhe was writing in a Cloſet, near her Chamber, <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> having taken her ſtation befor a Glaſs, to mend ſomething ſhe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lik'd in her dreſs, <hi>Givry</hi> followed her, and with a tone that ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently evidenced his fear and his trouble, ſaid, <q>
                  <hi>Mademoiſelle,</hi> may the Letter of my Lady Dutcheſs,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:58051:47"/>your Mother, be as favourable to me as another was unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate? and will it afford me the occaſion and means to know the particulars of my miſhap?</q> 
               <q>Let's talk no more of it, anſwers <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> interupting him, I declare my ſelf guilty of having occaſioned your raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. I thought we had not yet paſt the time of our Infancy, when the greateſt familiarities are innocent; but you were not of that opinion, but look'd on that as a favour which was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an effect of gayety and mirth, and thought you were allow'd to write a Love-Letter to one who had been ſo free with you as to ſend you Verſes of Love: I have ſacrificed the reſentment of that injury to the liberty of the Chevalier <hi>d'Oyſe,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd the King to think no more
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:58051:47"/>of it. Why ſhould you mind me of it?</q> 
               <q>But, <hi>Mademoiſelle,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plys <hi>Givry,</hi> if I never had the preſumption to write to you, and truth may merit from you what you have already granted due to the liberty of the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier <hi>d'Oyſe,</hi> ought you not to hear my defence? or will you deny me the juſtice of pleading for my ſelf?</q> 
               <q>How? did not you write to me? ſays <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle de Guiſe;</hi> the Letter was delivered me as yours, hath your Name ſubſcribed to it, and two or three meſſages have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed the boldneſs whereof it is full.</q> 
               <q>Having never ſeen it, anſwers <hi>Givry</hi> coldly, I know not what boldneſs you condemn in it; but know very well Ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver writ it: and thought I had a deſire to do it, yet I maſtered it; and it is impoſſible that the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:58051:48"/>Letter you mention ſhould have my Name in it of my write<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This Adventure appeared ſo ſtrange to <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> that ſhe reſolved to know the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of it; ſhe remembred that as ſhe was going to fling that Letter in the Fire, one of her Maids for whom ſhe had no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, having ſeen that Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Love, and found it hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomly written, had hept her from burning it: ſhe called for the Maid, and having ask'd what was become of that Paper, the Maid anſwered ſhe had it in a Box they had brought with them to <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours. Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> promiſed <hi>Givry</hi> a ſight of it that evening; and when the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs, her Mother, was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn, <hi>Givry</hi> having waited the young Princeſs to her Apartment,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:58051:48"/>ſhe kept her word with him. But how was he ſurpriz'd to find this Declaration of Love of the hand-wrighting of the Marqueſs <hi>de Bellegard?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>'Tis true he might have writ it, <hi>ſays</hi> Givry, <hi>having read it,</hi> but he ſhould have asked my leave; and this doubtleſs conceals a Myſtery I am afraid to diſcover.</q> 
               <q>Whence comes the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, anſwers <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> who could have impos'd on you ſentiments of ſuch extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant preſumption?</q> 
               <q>'Tis not that I complain of <hi>Mademoiſeelle,</hi> ſays <hi>Givry,</hi> the paſſion the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>de Bellegard</hi> attributes to me is too glorious to be denyed: But 'tis he hath written to you in my Name; and though it be true it was impoſſible for me to ſee you without adoring you, yet I would have dyed rather
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:58051:49"/>than have told you ſo: and the Marqueſs hath been falſe to the friendſhip between us, in diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering a ſecret I gave him no leave to reveal. But alas, adds he with a ſight, is this all the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood he is guilty of? did he not write to you in my Name, to ſound your thoughts for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Love is full of fancies and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricious extravagances. <hi>made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Guiſe</hi> was highly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens'd at the preſumption ſhe charged uon <hi>Givry;</hi> and what diſpleas'd her from him, ſhe had equal reaſon to be diſpleas'd with from any Gentleman of his Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in the Kingdom. There was not a comlier Perſon in <hi>France,</hi> nor any in ſo fair a way for the higheſt Preferments. Not to mention thoſe grounds and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> had to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:58051:49"/>own an eſteem and ſome kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for him. However, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an humour not to be paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd but in the extravagances of Love, ſhe look'd on this Action of the Marqueſs as ſingular, and entertain'd a more than ordinary curioſity to know what could move him to it. She asked <hi>Giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> ſeveral Queſtions, to diſcover whether <hi>Bellegard</hi> had only ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for his Friend, or wrote with an intention to know whether ſhe would receive the Love of any but a Prince. This laſt ſurmiſe pleas'd her better than the firſt; and though ſhe appear'd haughty, and feign'd her ſelf willing to find out <hi>Bellegard</hi>'s Crime, for no other end but to puniſh it, 'tis certain the rarity of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture made her look upon it with a more favourable Eye, than ſhe had done the Letter at firſt.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:58051:50"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Givry</hi> preceiv'd nothing of this, ſcarce daring to caſt his Eyes on the Princeſs; and though her looks might have given him ſome cauſe of ſuſpicion, the ſenſe he had of her haughtineſs obliged him to believe the contrary. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſhe appear'd highly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked at his preſumption, and ſometimes did but laugh at it. Though ſhe equally mortifi'd <hi>Giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>'s hopes either way; yet the thoughts of his having made a Perſonal diſcovery of his Love to <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> gave him ſome comfort; and the night af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this diſcourſe was the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanteſt he had ſince the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Corbeil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Madam <hi>de Guiſe</hi> parted on the morrow betimes; and <hi>Givry</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving accompanied her as far as he could, left the care of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to his Lieutenant <hi>de
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:58051:50"/>Roy,</hi> and went to <hi>Giſors,</hi> where he was ſure to find the Marqueſs <hi>de Bellegard.</hi> He had not ſeen him ſince the buſineſs of <hi>Corbeil;</hi> and at that time he was gone to meet the ſuccours ſent the King by the Proteſtant Princes of <hi>Almain,</hi> under the Conduct of Prince <hi>Caſimir,</hi> who was already come into <hi>France</hi> with the Prince of <hi>Conde.</hi> The King fearing the Forces of the League might lay an Ambuſh for them, had ſent the Marqueſs <hi>de Bellegard</hi> to ſcowr the ways; and at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn <hi>Givry</hi> was wounded, and gone to <hi>Brie.</hi> He was impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for a ſight of him, to ask him the meaning of the Letter; and found him honoured with a new Dignity, the King having made him Duke and Peer, for which he was receiving the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements of his Friends, as <hi>Givry</hi> arrived.</p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:58051:51"/>
            <p> The new Duke ran to him with open Arms; and though <hi>Givry</hi> was not ſatisfied with his proceedings, he forbore not to make his Careſſes an obliging re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn. They fell in diſcourſe. The Duke told his Friend, that they expected at <hi>Giſors</hi> the Princeſs <hi>Katherine,</hi> the Kings Siſter, who having been under his Majeſties diſpleaſure, for having deſign'd a marriage with Count <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> contrary to his Majeſties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, had newly received par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for her diſobedience, and came, as was reported, to give her conſent to another marriage: All the diſcourſe at Court was of the reception prepared for her. But after this general Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Givry</hi> finding himſelf alone with the new Duke, <q>I have News to tell you too, ſayes he to the Duke, Madam and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:58051:51"/>de Guiſe</hi> coming with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my Province, the latter charged me with an Anſwer to a a Letter you had written to her.</q> The Duke <hi>de Bellegard</hi> redden'd, and <hi>Givry</hi> having obſerved it; <q>I did not think, <hi>ſays he,</hi> I had ſo conſiderable a Perſon as you to my Secretary, and ſhould have done my utmoſt to avoid gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you that trouble, had it been in my power to fancy you would have vouchſafed to have taken it upon you.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Do you find my Letter did you any harm, anſwered the Duke, or think you it was not the Office of a Friend to put you in condition of ſpeakiag to <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Lover?</q> 
               <q>I am not yet ſatisfied, reply'd <hi>Givry</hi> coldly, whether that Declaration was to my advantage, or prejudice:
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:58051:52"/>But, my Lord Duke, I know it the part of a true Friend, not to have done any thing of this nature without my conſent; and I have cauſe to believe you were willing to make me try a dangerous Foord, rather than ſave me another kind of peril. This, in tuth, is ingeniouſly turn'd, ſays the Duke <hi>de Belle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</hi> ironically, how many Lovers have you ſeen carry on their amours with the Ladies they Court, by acquainting them with the paſſion of their Rivals?</q> 
               <q>What then did you deſign by it, replys <hi>Givry</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd in his ſuſpicion by the trouble he ſaw the Duke in, being of a temper too frank and open for diſguiſe?) What right had you to diſcover my ſecret, or what excuſe can you make to the deareſt of your Friends,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:58051:52"/>for having drawn upon him the indignation of a Perſon he had confeſt to you he was in Love with?</q> 
               <q>When I conſidered, ſays the Duke <hi>de Bellegard,</hi> the Circumſtances of your Love, I was of opinion you might long languiſh without knowing your deſtiny; and eſteeming uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty the moſt miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of a Lover, I was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to bring you out of it, and perſwade you to deſiſt or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue your Amour according to occaſion: if <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> hath favourably received the Declaration of your flames, you are ungrateful to entertain my ſervice with ſo much cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; if ſhe be really angry with you, I have left you at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to diſavow the Letter; and you may either make uſe of your reaſon for your Cure, or
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:58051:53"/>continue to love her without telling her of it, as if I had not written.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> was very good-natur'd, and a great lover of the Duke <hi>de Bellegard,</hi> he was ready to beg his pardon for having ſuſpected him; and had done it, but that they were interrupted by a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Courtiers who came pouring in upon them, and that very Evening he became ſenſible that his friendſhip blinded him, and that the <hi>Duke de Bellegard</hi> was really his Rival.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>de Maugiron</hi> faithfully executed the threats ſhe had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt of loving <hi>Givry</hi> all her Life, whether he would or not. The ſlights of her Lover, and the homage ſhe received every day from ſeveral others, could not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her affection. She made ſo diligent inquiry among thoſe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:58051:53"/>that went to <hi>Moulins,</hi> whither Queen <hi>Louiſe</hi> was retired upon the death of the late King, and had placed ſo many ſpyes about <hi>Givry,</hi> that ſhe made diſcovery of his Love for <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe:</hi> there was ſome diſcourſe of it upon the ſetting at liberty the <hi>Chevalier d'Oyſe;</hi> and the ſtory of the Letter, which <hi>Givry</hi> aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red he had not written, could not be kept ſo cloſe but this jealous Lover knew ſomething of it: And in the journey the <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe</hi> Dowager of <hi>Nemours</hi> made to <hi>Bourbon,</hi> Madam <hi>de Maugiron,</hi> who ſaw her there, gain'd her Love ſo far that when Queen <hi>Louiſe</hi> changed the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes of the world for the Solitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of a Cloyſter, Madam <hi>de Nemours</hi> took Madam <hi>Maugiron</hi> into her family. She was there when Madam and <hi>Mademoiſelle
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:58051:54"/>de Guiſe</hi> came to <hi>Nemours.</hi> The young <hi>Princeſs</hi> and Madam <hi>de Maugiron</hi> look'd upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a great deal of Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs and attention, and this latter, being poſſeſt with jealouſie, was ſo diligent to ſpy out an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to diſcover the ſentiments of her Rival, that ſhe learnt them from her own mouth. The ſickneſs of Madam <hi>de Nemours</hi> was rather tedious than dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> being not obliged to any great appearances of ſorrow, took the liberty frequently to leave the <hi>Ducheſſe</hi> her Mother to take care of the ſick Lady. Being retir'd timely one evening to her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and going thence to take a walk in the Garden, without other company but a Maid, who was her confident, Madam <hi>de Maugiron</hi> follow'd them, and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58051:54"/>having ſlipp'd in behind the Pales, heard <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> ſay,</p>
            <p>No, <hi>la Mothe,</hi> I do not think the Maſter of the Horſe hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomer than <hi>Givry,</hi> and I have confeſt to you more than once, that I had retained ſuch an Idea of this latter as might have incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me to much tenderneſs for him, had he been of Quality ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to mine. But whether this humor of mine were over when I ſaw him again, or that his friend, being a newer Object to me, had the happineſs to diſcern bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the weakneſs of our Sex, and make his attack with greater ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, I was more attentive to him than to <hi>Givry</hi> in the <hi>Tuille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi> What he did during the Truce pleas'd me more than what <hi>Givry</hi> did, though I gave <hi>Givry</hi> marks of kindeneſſes and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:58051:55"/>
               <q>I durſt not have given <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legard,</hi> without trouble and ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. When I received the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you know of, I thought I had ſeen him that brought it in <hi>Bellegard</hi>'s Train; I believed it had come from him, and was ſo vext to find another Name ſubſcribed, it angred me more againſt <hi>Givry</hi> than the Crime he appear'd guilty of. Not that I could have been willing <hi>Belle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</hi> ſhould have ſpoken to me of Love, without reſentment on my part, but that (the Rules of Reſpect and Decency ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd) it would have pleas'd me better to diſcover <hi>Bellegard,</hi> than <hi>Givry,</hi> in Love with me: And I muſt confeſs I found in my ſelf a more than ordinary joy, when I thought at <hi>Melun</hi> I was Miſtreſs of his affection.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>But, <hi>Mademoiſelle,</hi> ſays <hi>la
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:58051:55"/>Mothe,</hi> what aſſurance have you of that? the Letter was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in <hi>Givry</hi>'s Name; and the Maſter of the Horſe, being his particular Friend, had perhaps no other intention, but to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Love to you, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing him to your diſpleaſure. Either thou haſt no wit, replys <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> or thou doſt not believe as thou ſay'ſt. Call to mind the Actions of <hi>Bellegard</hi> during the Treaty: remember his looks, and the Meſſages he ſent me every day; and thoſe Verſes of the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Lover every day on my Toillette, or among my Cloaths. It was not <hi>Givry</hi> that wrote them, therefore it was <hi>Belle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard.</hi> There is not one of our Party pretends any engagements, being all my Kindred or my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours; and either cannot,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:58051:56"/>or dare not love me. <hi>Bellegard</hi> and <hi>Givry</hi> are the ſole Perſons of the Kings Party have declar'd themſelves engag'd, the one confeſſing he is in Love with me, the other having written me a myſterious Letter. Whatever comes under the Character of Paſſion, proceeds doubtleſs from one of them. It is not <hi>Givry</hi> hath made the Declaration of Love to me, therefore it muſt be <hi>Bellegard,</hi> who had the dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity to learn by anothers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience how I might be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to entertain his affection.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> as ſhe was ſpeaking theſe words, came into a Walk where Madam <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giron</hi> could not follow her with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being perceived; but ſhe had heard enough, and was impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to let <hi>Givry</hi> know on the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the fruit of his unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:58051:56"/>to her; and fearing her Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not of force to perſwade him, ſhe pretended buſineſs at Court, and arrived there as <hi>Givry</hi> was coming out of the Duke <hi>de Belle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</hi>'s Lodgings.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>de Maugiron</hi>'s thoughts being all fixt on <hi>Givry,</hi> ſhe went in ſearch of him only and eaſily found him: He received a Billet from her to inform him of her arrival, and deſire the favour of ſeeing him preſently. This News troubled him, he dreaded the ſight of her, and could have found in his heart to return ſtrait to his Government; but bethink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf how uncivil it would appear to uſe a Perſon thus, who had not given occaſion for it, he maſter'd his reluctance, and went to the place where Madam <hi>de Maugiron</hi> had aſſign'd him.</p>
            <p>Never did the appear ſo hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:58051:57"/>and ſo fine, as that Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and <hi>Givry</hi> was aſtoniſht that with ſo many Charms and ſo much Love, it had not been in her power to retain him her Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and thinking ſhe was come only to reproach him.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Save your ſelf the trouble of telling me the occaſion of your Journey, Madam, <hi>ſays he,</hi> I part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gueſs at it, and know before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand what your juſt reſentment may dictate to you. But, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, I am a Wretch that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enjoy favours of this kind, nor cure my ſelf of my Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, though I blame my ſelf for it. Slight me as I deſerve, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, and extend not your good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſo far as to reproach me for my inconſtancy, but give me o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver as loſt to my lukewarmneſs and indifference.</q> 
               <q>I could real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give you over to them, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:58051:57"/>Madam <hi>de Maugiron,</hi> were they my only Rivals. 'Tis poſſible my affection might car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry me ſo far, as to rejoice at your happineſs, though attended with my misfortunes, and I might pardon you for being in Love with <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> did ſhe vouchſafe to anſwer it on her part; but I cannot give you up to her ſlights, and the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery of your Friend <hi>Bellegard.</hi> Theſe are the Enemies you are to provide your defence againſt, rather than the reproaches which the kindneſs I retain for you will not permit me to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you with.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> was ſurpriz'd at this diſcourſe, and was within little of letting her ſee the trouble he was in: But bethinking himſelf, that Madam <hi>Maugiron</hi> had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure by ſome Spyes diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:58051:58"/>ſomething of the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but knew not the whole truth, he recover'd himſelf, and anſwered coldly, <q>I cannot won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Madam, that a Lady of your merit ſhould ſeek the cauſe of my indifference elſewhere than in your ſelf; and am ſenſible, that, ſuſpecting the beſt of my Friends hath not ſufficiently op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the injuſtice I am guilty of towards you, you would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge your ſelf of him by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging us in a quarrel: But, Madam, I am not ſuſceptible of ſuch ill impreſſions; and what I know of your miſtakes as to <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> makes me think you no leſs mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken as to the Duke <hi>de Belle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard.</hi>
               </q> 
               <q>No, no, ſays Madam <hi>de Maugiron,</hi> you need not affect theſe diſguiſes with me. I know what I ſay, and heard it
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:58051:58"/>from the Mouth of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe.</hi>
               </q> And ſo telling him of what paſt at <hi>Bourbon</hi> and <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours,</hi> ſhe put him into ſo furious a jealouſie that he could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal it from her.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Pardon me, Madam, <hi>ſays he,</hi> confeſſing it, that I make you the Witneſs of a tranſport, which cannot but be troubleſome to you. Had I power enough o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my ſelf to moderate it, I ſhould have had power enough to maſter the cauſe of it; and I ſhould love you again as ardent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as formerly. If ſwear to you, by that which I hold moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, that I wiſh at the coſt of the beſt part of my blood I had continued conſtant to my firſt Paſſion. But, Madam, Love goes not by choice, the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of affection tyranize over Reaſon: And ſince 'tis in vain
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:58051:59"/>to deny my inconſtancy, I muſt declare I love <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> even to madneſs; and am capable of the worſt effects of deſpair, if I ſee her prefer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me a Rival of my Quality. Perhaps I ſhould not grudge to ſee her marry ſome great Prince, but it will be certain death to me to ſee her pleas'd with the addreſſes of another Man of my Quality: if it be true ſhe is pleas'd with them, you will not be long unreveng'd, but ſhall ſee the effects of the unhappy News you have brought me ſo far.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As he ſaid this he went out, and having tormented himſelf all night, went in the morning to the Duke <hi>de Bellegard</hi> before he was awake. <q>You have reaſon, <hi>ſays he,</hi> opening the Curtain, to ſleep quietly, you may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:58051:59"/>the pleaſure of ſound reſt and repoſe; I muſt bid it fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel. But, perfideous Friend, why did you not deprive me of it the ordinary way? or what have I done to make you ſo trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous as to render me the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of my own torment? 'Twas by the blindneſs of my confidence, you had the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to ſee the firſt effects of the Excellencies of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe.</hi> 'Twas I firſt brought you to <hi>Paris</hi> during the Treaty: 'Twas by the permiſſion I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of the King you had the convenience of treating her in the Camp: 'Tis my Name you made uſe of for declaring your Love: 'Twas by the miſtake you ingag'd her in, you obliged me to tell her firſt that Letter was yours. Was ſhe the only Perſon you could affect? or if
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:58051:60"/>it was impoſſible to ſee her with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out falling in Love with her, had you no other way to diſcover your love but by uſing my name?</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Duke <hi>de Bellegard</hi> might, if he had pleas'd, have baffled longer with <hi>Givry,</hi> the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Madam <hi>Maugiron</hi> had made were not convincing. But his conſcience accuſed him, and he confeſt ingeniouſly to <hi>Givry,</hi> that he was in love with <hi>Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle de Guiſe,</hi> that he had been ſo from the firſt view he had of her in the <hi>Tuilleries,</hi> that his love increas'd with the time, and that to ſound her affection he had written the Letter <hi>Givry</hi> had ſeen. Had ſhe given you an obliging anſwer, I had us'd ſuch endeavours to maſter my affections, that perhaps I ſhould have conquer'd it. But ſince ſhe is not pre-ingaged in favour to you,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:58051:60"/>give me leave to Court an affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction you have no right to, and remember, that if any engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could have been proof a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the charms of <hi>Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle de Guiſe,</hi> Madam <hi>de Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giron</hi> had ſaved you the trouble of another <hi>Amour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They had much other diſcourſe to this purpoſe, and began to fall into very ſharp language, which would not have permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to part as good friends as formerly, had not the Duke <hi>de Montpenſier</hi> interrupted them. He perceived them in a heat, and obſerved indignation in their looks. And the tranſports of jealouſie are commonly impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, ſo that <hi>Givry</hi> was not long, but the Duke <hi>de Montpenſier</hi> from his looks and his actions might clearly conclude what he gueſs'd at firſt ſight, <hi>Givry</hi> named
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:58051:61"/>no body, and the Duke <hi>de Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſier</hi> underſtood no more, but that they were fallen out about a matter of love. But the King, who preſently heard of the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, being throughly acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Givry</hi>'s affair, ſent for him, and made ſo good uſe of the power he had over him, that he quieted his ſpirits, and calmed the diſorder they were in.</p>
            <p>What ſucceſs have you had in your addreſſes to <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> ſayes the King, that you think you ſelf concerned to make good your right to her againſt a Rival. If either of you be one day ſo fortunate as to obtain any favour from her, I may perhaps diſpenſe with the others diſpair, but till then what cauſe have you of diſpute, or what is't you quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Givry</hi> was ready to tell the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:58051:61"/>King he had cauſe to envy his Rival; but forbore out of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect he had for <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> and his unwillingneſs to declare the happineſs of the Duke <hi>de Bellegard;</hi> the ſecret knowledge whereof ſufficiently tormented him, without the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of open publication. So that he choſe rather to ſay no more, than barely aſſure his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, he would not give the example of diviſion among the Chiefs of his Party.</p>
            <p>The better to keep his word, he return'd to his Government, where the King was to come ſhortly, and order was to be given for his Majeſty's reception. Before he left Court he ſaw the Princeſs <hi>Catherine</hi> arriv'd, and prevail'd with his Majeſty that ſhe ſhould take Madam <hi>Maugiron</hi> to her, as Queen <hi>Louiſe</hi> had done, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:58051:62"/>a Penſion for her, that ſhe might maintain her ſelf with more ſplendour at Court. And could ſhe have contented her ſelf with friendſhip from him, and a more than ordinary care for her fortune, ſhe would have reſted ſatisfi'd with <hi>Givry</hi>'s proceeding: But all was nothing to her if it fell ſhort of Love, and whatever ſhe could do, it was impoſſible to kindle it again in his heart.</p>
            <p>They had ſeveral diſcourſes on this ſubject, which deſerve rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to make out the extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Love. You will come again to me one day, ſays ſhe to him, and 'tis impoſſible but ſo much love and conſtancy as I have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt for you will affect you at laſt, you will learn the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between a Love like mine, and that of a young Lady that knows not what Love is. You
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:58051:62"/>will wonder you have been ſo long in coming to the knowledge of it. You will then be aſhamed of your blindneſs, and willing to repair your fault, by loving again with greater ardency than at firſt. Never fancy it, anſwers <hi>Givry,</hi> Love that dyes of it ſelf, never comes to life again in a man of my age. I ſee clearly at this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, all that time could diſcover to me. I confeſs you deſerve a heart more faithful than mine, and that I am unjuſt to requite your kindneſs ſo ill. But in Love, our underſtanding hath no power over affection. And if I muſt declare the height of indifference, I verily believe I ſhould ſooner love a third perſon, than return again to you. This is a hard ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet I think it worſe to amuſe you with vain hopes any longer. Proceed yet further, replyes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:58051:63"/>
               <hi>Maugiron</hi> with tears, and tell me thou hateſt me more than ever thou lovedſt me. I ſhall not love thee the leſs for it. My fatal paſſion can ſubſiſt without hope, and ſeems long ſince to gather new ſtrength without it. Thou art not beholding to me for it. 'Tis no voluntary love, yet ſure thou ſhould have ſome pity for me, whom my Stars uſe with ſuch extremity of rigor.</p>
            <p>He had done much, and would have done any thing to ſee this Lady diſengaged. But it is not ſo eaſie to be cured of this diſeaſe, as to fall into it. She continued lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him in ſpite of him, and he return'd to <hi>Melun</hi> as unjuſt and ungrateful, as ſhe had found him at <hi>Giſors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Voyage the King made into <hi>Brie,</hi> was a happy ſtep to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the peace of the Kingdom.
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:58051:63"/>The people grew weary of the wars, and the Duke of <hi>Mayne</hi> was particularly concern'd to put an end to it. The laſt Expedition the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> made into <hi>France,</hi> he highly careſs'd the young Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi> The <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſaid aloud, <q>That a perſon of his age and activity was fitter to head a Party againſt the King, than a General that grew old, and had not his health.</q> The <hi>Ducheſſe</hi> of <hi>Mayne</hi> trembled at the apprehenſion theſe diſcourſes might take effect. She knew Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Guiſe</hi> a haughthy <hi>Princeſs,</hi> and one would uſe her according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if her Son became head of the League, and ſhe thought it better ſubmit to the King, than ſee her husband commanded by a young man. She hung conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the Dukes <hi>Ears,</hi> to incline him to an accommodation while
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:58051:64"/>he was in power, and made him fear he could not make it ſo much to his advantage, when deveſted of his Authority. He reliſh'd this advice well enough; but it could not take effect, while the King continued Proteſtant: and his Majeſty being, in that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, of the ſame opinion with his Enemies, had taken a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to be inſtructed in the Popiſh Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>A Truce was agreed upon for three Months, during which his Majeſty being advanced as far as <hi>Melun,</hi> Conferences were held with more ſincerity than former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on the Leagues part. The Conferences were no ſooner o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, but Madam, and <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Guiſe</hi> paſſed the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time into <hi>Brie,</hi> in their way to <hi>Paris,</hi> and carried with them the Dutcheſs <hi>Dowager</hi> of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours</hi>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:58051:64"/>in a Litter. They ſaw not the King: Madam <hi>de Guiſe</hi> fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing if ſhe waited on his Majeſty, the Duke of <hi>Mayenne</hi> would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach her with it. But the King complemented her by <hi>Giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> who accompanying them to the Gates of <hi>Paris,</hi> found an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity as he came from Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to ſpeak a few words to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle de Guiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>May I adventure, <hi>Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle,</hi> ſays he, to ask if you have at laſt done me the juſtice my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence deſerves, and defaced out of your heart thoſe impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of wrath a forged Letter ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſed me to?</q> 
               <q>You have not diſown'd any thing that Letter contained, anſwered <hi>Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle</hi> coldly; it was not the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter diſpleas'd me, but the Senſe.</q> 
               <q>I do, and muſt ever own, <hi>ſays</hi> Givry, I have a love
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:58051:65"/>for you, that extends to adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but I diſown the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs taken to diſcover it ſo ſoon. I would have kept it cloſe with abundance of reſpect in my heart, until ſome eminent ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice ſhould have in ſome ſort authoriz'd me to own it; and if my ill fortune would have deny'd me the happineſs of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver being uſeful to you, I would have waited for death to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piate my temerity.</q> 
               <q>All this might have been eaſily done, replies <hi>Mademoiſelle,</hi> with like tone as before; had you but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd the Love you were char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with, I ſhould not have been at any pains to convince you of it.</q> 
               <q>But, <hi>Mademoiſelle,</hi> ſays <hi>Givry,</hi> it was you ſpoke to me, you who are my viſible Goddeſs. I owe you the duty of a religious ſincerity, and
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:58051:65"/>had I endeavoured to diſguiſe it, my Eyes would have diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered it.</q> 
               <q>To what end is this diſcourſe, ſays the Princeſs, with ſome frowardneſs, I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed the King, and promiſe you once more, not to think of what is paſt. Let me de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you, once for all, not to ſpeak of it while we live.</q> 
               <q>I thought, replys <hi>Givory,</hi> cut with grief to the heart, you gave me no ſuch order at <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lun, Mademoiſelle;</hi> give me leave to tell you, you had then ſome curioſity which made this diſcourſe reliſh better, or that you reflected on it ſince to my diſadvantage.</q> 
               <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> bluſh'd at <hi>Givory</hi>'s reproach, which confirming the truth of Madam <hi>de Maugiron</hi>'s report, <q>Ha, cryes he, tranſported with jealouſie, 'tis but too true that
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:58051:66"/>the raſhneſs I am ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for, is excuſed in my Rival; and that I am the moſt unhappy of Lovers.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As he was ſaying this, word was brought <hi>mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> ſhe muſt come away; and ſhe took ſo little pleaſure in <hi>Giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>'s diſcourſe, ſhe made not her Company ſtay for her. <hi>Givry</hi> brought her to the Coach, and followed it two hours after; but ſcarce in all that time could Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Guiſe</hi> draw four words from him. He returned to the King ſo troubled and melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that his Majeſty perceived it, and had the goodneſs to take him aſide, and ask him what made him ſo ſad. <q>Ah, Sir, replys <hi>Givry,</hi> almoſt with tears in his eyes, <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> hates me; and if the reſpect I owe her may allow me to ſay more, ſhe
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:58051:66"/>loves the Duke <hi>de Bellegard.</hi>
               </q> The King was willing to know what grounds he had for this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, and the afflicted Lover was not able to forbear the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very. <q>The fancies and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of a young Perſon whoſe affection is not fixt, ſays the King, are as changeable as they are wild. <hi>Bellegard</hi> is no more in a condition to marry her than you are, nor can entertain any hopes but of pleaſing her: And ſince he has no other, I will find out ſo many occaſions you may make uſe of to that end, that you ſhall at laſt be the happier of the two. But, for my ſake, be at peace with him, and leave the reſt to me.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This promiſe gave <hi>Givry</hi> ſome comfort, knowing it in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's power to put him in a way, to do <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> ſo
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:58051:67"/>many ſervices, that her gratitude to him might one day overcome the favour ſhe was prepoſſeſt with towards <hi>Bellegard.</hi> This made him ſacrifice the motions of his jealouſie to the pleaſure of a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſo familiar and obliging; ſo that there hapned nothing ſharper between theſe Lovers at <hi>Melun,</hi> than at <hi>Giſors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time the general Peace of the Kingdom advanced, by the King's embracing the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Profeſſion; who having ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd the Proteſtant at St. <hi>Denys,</hi> ſaw the obſtacle of his reception remov'd, and <hi>Paris</hi> opening her Gates to him as her lawful Prince.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Mayenne,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes of his Houſe, reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> where they after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards made their peace. And there remained of them at <hi>Paris</hi>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:58051:67"/>only the Dowager of <hi>Nemours,</hi> being too weak for a remove; and <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> who would not leave her. The King, to keep his word with <hi>Givry,</hi> us'd him his Inſtrument for the daily favours he did the Family of <hi>Guiſe;</hi> he gave him the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Forces ordered for the ſafe Conduct of the Duke of <hi>Mayenne.</hi> And when his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty made his Triumphant Entry into <hi>Paris,</hi> he gave <hi>Givry</hi> leave, with a Brigade of his Archers, to Guard the Houſe of Madam <hi>de Nemours</hi> from violence; not that there was any great cauſe to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend dangers, in a City that had made a voluntary ſubmiſſion to its undoubted Soveraign, but that the Houſe of <hi>Guiſe</hi> having been the ſupport of the League, it could not be expected but there might be, among the People,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:58051:68"/>ſome ill diſpoſed perſons, who under pretence of zeal for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's intereſts, might endeavor to enrich themſelves by pillage of a houſe belonging to a family ſo eminently engag'd againſt the King; ſo that his Majeſty thought it neceſſary to uſe this precaution, and committed the care and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of it to <hi>Givry.</hi> He ran in all haſte to execute his orders, and acquit himſelf of his Charge, with all the Offers of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and kindneſs that might be expected from a Lover. But was extremely ſurpriz'd, to ſee himſelf prevented by the Duke <hi>de Belle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard,</hi> whom he found at the head of a great Body of Volunteers, ordering a <hi>Corps de Garde</hi> to be ſet at the Gate of the <hi>Hoſtel de Nemours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who gave you order for this, ſays <hi>Givry</hi> all in a rage; and how
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:58051:68"/>comes it you preſume of your own head to place <hi>Corps de Garde</hi> in any part of the Town. I will give the King an account of what I do, ſays <hi>Bellegarde</hi> cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it belongs not to you to take notice of it. It ſo far belongs to me, replys <hi>Givry,</hi> that if you give them not inſtantly orders to draw of, I will preſently fall on, and we ſhall ſee hereafter whoſe actions will be beſt approved by his Majeſty. You forget the rights of our ancient friendſhip, ſays the Duke, and will make me at length forget what we have been, to mind you what we are. I will refreſh your memory, ſays <hi>Givry</hi> laying his hand on his Sword, and 'tis becauſe we have been too intimate friends, we are now become irreconcileable Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. With that, the two Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals, forgetting the Kings orders,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:58051:69"/>fell upon one another with unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel'd fury, and had not long fought without leaving bloudy marks of their combat, if <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> (who ſpy'd from a window the beginning of the quarrel) had not come in perſon to ſtop it. She ruſht in courageouſly between the two Rivals, and having calmed their fury by her preſence, ſhe had no ſooner commanded them to be quiet, but they laid their Swords at her feet. What, ſays ſhe harſhly to <hi>Givry,</hi> are you he that oppoſes the care taken for our ſafety? it was not enough for you to have fought againſt the children of the late Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> but you muſt expoſe his Mother and daughter to pillage, and by this viſible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude hope to eſtabliſh your ſelf in my favor. I, <hi>Mademoiſelle,</hi> anſwers <hi>Givry</hi> paſſionately, am I
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:58051:69"/>guilty of ingratitude to you? or would I expoſe you to pillage? What elſe would you have done? replys <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe:</hi> what means what I have but now ſeen and heard? You have ſeen me jealous any other but I ſhould do you this ſmall ſervice, ſays <hi>Givry,</hi> and to my deſperate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfort I ſee you angry at my hindring another to do it. I will not admit ti to be done by the one or the other of you, anſwers <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle de Guiſe;</hi> ſend back your men, and come not hither to give ill people and Robbers an example of impunity; we ſhall guard our ſelves better without you, than with the aſſiſtance of two perſons who have ſo little reſpect for us. This ſaid, ſhe impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly commanded both Parties to draw off, and the two Chiefs were forced to give them order
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:58051:70"/>accordingly, but made them keep thereabouts, and ſtaid in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with the Princeſſes to ſecure them from outrage. They needed not this caution long, for the King was ſcarce entred <hi>Paris</hi> but all was calmed, and a quiet eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed as if there had never been any diſorder there. His Majeſty was ſafe at <hi>Noſtre - Dame,</hi> and came thence to dinner at the <hi>Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vre,</hi> where the moſt zealous of his Subjects paid him their firſt homage: after dinner the King went to ſee March out a Garriſon of <hi>Spaniards</hi> the Leaguers had taken in, and provided by the Treaty they ſhould have a Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port from his Majeſty: in the mean time the Brigadier, who accompanied <hi>Givry</hi> with the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the Guard, gave his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty an account of what paſt between the Lovers; the King
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:58051:70"/>ſent from them, and charged them ſo ſtrictly not to quarrel for the future, that they never after had the confidence to do it.</p>
            <p>All the actions of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> had confirm'd <hi>Givry</hi> in the knowledge of his misfortune. She admitted more eaſily the Duke <hi>de Bellegard</hi>'s excuſes than his. All her ſharp language was directed to <hi>Givry,</hi> all her good words addreſſed to <hi>Bellegarde:</hi> when <hi>Bellegarde</hi> fixt his eyes upon hers, ſhe appear'd pleaſed. <hi>Givry</hi> could meet nothing in her looks, but indignation and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. The diſpleaſure this caus'd him, robbed him of his good humor, and altered his very countenance ſo far, that the King was afraid he would fall dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly ill. His Majeſty who lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him intirely, and was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible of the torments of Love,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:58051:71"/>did all in his power to comfort him. He had the goodneſs to viſit <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> and to ſpeak to her in his favor. When the Duke of <hi>Mayenne</hi> made any Propoſitions, the King would not receive them, but by the mouth of <hi>Givry,</hi> and gave him full power to treat with the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and made him ſole Mediator between his Majeſty and thoſe Princes.</p>
            <p>But all theſe favors of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty were ill interpreted. <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Guiſe</hi> thought <hi>Givry</hi> had begged them, and was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd with him, as having made her the Subject of diſcourſe for the King and the whole Court. But that was not the ſole cauſe of her diſcontent, the King had thought her handſom, and ſhe had ambition enough to carry her as high as the Throne: And
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:58051:71"/>they diſcourſed already of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the King's Marriage with Queen <hi>Margaret,</hi> as a matter reſolved. The Duke <hi>de Bellegard</hi> having many intrigues, and knowing how to make uſe of all his advantages, let <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> know how ſerviceable he might be to promote her deſigns, and dextrouſly dropt words which might make her appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend <hi>Givry</hi>'s love as an obſtacle; that the King had a love for him, and probably his kindneſs for <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vry</hi> might prevail more with him than <hi>Mademoiſelle</hi>'s Charms: the Duke <hi>de Bellegarde</hi> carried on his affairs by theſe deviſes ſo well, that <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> was ſcarce civil to <hi>Givry.</hi> The Princeſs <hi>Catherine</hi> (as well as Madam <hi>Gabrielle,</hi> and the reſt of the Court) was now come to <hi>Paris,</hi> and had brought Madam
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:58051:72"/>
               <hi>Maugiron</hi> with her. This Lady us'd all poſſible endeavours to make her advantage of the rigors of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe:</hi> But it was her fate, as well as the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate <hi>Givry</hi>'s, to love where they were not belov'd; and were ſo far from being cured by the ſlights put upon them, that their paſſion was heightned thereby.</p>
            <p>The firſt two Months after <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> was reduced, the King em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in eſtabliſhing the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament there, iſſuing gracious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations in favour of his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Subjects, and receiving the Deputies of <hi>Roan,</hi> and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Towns, returning to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the Crown: But about the end of that time the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> deſpairing of being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to raiſe more domeſtick broils in <hi>France,</hi> attack'd it from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:58051:72"/>
               <hi>La Capelle,</hi> and his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty foreſeeing that if the Enemy made any progreſs in <hi>France,</hi> the reſt of the Leaguers would take courage afreſh, went in Perſon to raiſe the Siege, but underſtood by the way the Town was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred; and deſirous to repair this loſs by ſome Conqueſt, he deſigned to beſiege <hi>Laon,</hi> being as a Fort for the remnant of the League. The Duke of <hi>Mayenne</hi> was then of the number; the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> had made his peace, and moſt of the Princes of his Houſe followed his Example: but the Duke of <hi>Mayenne</hi> had inſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſcruples, and would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the King, till he ſhould have abſolution from <hi>Rome;</hi> and keeping the Field under that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, countenanced and ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Enemies undertakings. The King having advertiſement
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:58051:73"/>that the Duke's Children were at <hi>Laon,</hi> with ſome other of the moſt obſtinate Leaguers, thought the taking that place would more eaſily oblige the reſt of the Party to implore his mercy. But to prevent the reproach of not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving try'd fair means before force, he let the Princeſſes of the Houſe of <hi>Lorrain</hi> underſtand, that he was conſtrain'd to proceed with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity againſt the reſt of the Leaguers; and ſhould be very glad if they could ſeparate from the reſt of the Princes of their blood. He lov'd <hi>Givry</hi> too well to give this Commiſſion to any other but him. The King gave him his orders, and having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to make haſte, <hi>Givry</hi> was at the <hi>Hoſtel de Guiſe</hi> on the morrow before Noon. There he found <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> alone, the Dutcheſs her Mother
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:58051:73"/>being gone upon a piece of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, wherein ſhe was pleas'd to diſpenſe with the attendance of her Daughter. And <hi>Givry</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſent the young Princeſs word, he came from the King on buſineſs of importance, was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into her Chamber before ſhe was out of Bed. He found her ſo handſome in that poſture, that he was not able to maſter his Tranſport, but fell on his Knees at her Bed-ſide, and taking one of her hands kiſſed it, with that ardour, that he had preſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what further, if the the Princeſs had not thruſt him back, ſaying to him with an imperious tone; <q>You inſolent Fellow, do you make uſe of the King's Name, to come hither to offend me; get you out of my Chamber, and preſume not to ſet foot there again, till you have learnt better
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:58051:74"/>how you ought to demean your ſelf towards a Princeſs of my Rank.</q> Theſe words ſtruck <hi>Givry</hi> into ſuch aſtoniſhment, that he ſtood leaning againſt a Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow like one in a Trance; which <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as a diſobedience to her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, ſhe renewed her orders, and accompanied them with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of ſo much ſlight and contempt, that <hi>Givry</hi> could no longer endure them. <q>Yes, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle,</hi> ſays he with an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſuitable to his deſpair, you ſhall be obey'd; the preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Givry</hi> ſhall never more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your Chamber, and ſince he cannot live without ſeeing you, his blood ſhall expiate the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune of his having diſpleas'd you.</q>
            </p>
            <p>With that he went out. Had the officious <hi>La Mothe</hi> been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:58051:74"/>he ſhould have been ſtaid; but <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> for reaſons known to her ſelf, would not credit her, ſo that her Prayers and Remonſtrances were all in vain; and all ſhe could obtain, was that ſhe might ſeek him out, and ſay from her ſelf what ſhe thought proper to comfort him.</p>
            <p>She found him in the Garden at the <hi>Hoſtel de Guiſe,</hi> walking as one diſtracted; and making up to him, <q>What did you think on, <hi>ſays ſhe,</hi> when you us'd towards <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> liberties ſo condemnable, and altogether unfit? was that your way to obtain the favour of a Princeſs ſo vertuous and haughty? or did you look upon her as a Town you were reſolv'd to take by aſſault?</q> 
               <q>It was not well, anſwers <hi>Givry</hi> faintly, I
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:58051:75"/>confeſs my tranſport conſulted neither my reſpect nor my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but one look of <hi>Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle de Guiſe</hi> would have mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me of my duty, without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that torrent of ſlighting expreſſions. A paſſionate acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in a Man deſperately in Love, is not perhaps a Crime ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable as <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> hath judged it; but the reaſon is, that every thing is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive that is done by a Lover diſlik'd. 'Tis my Perſon, not my Love, diſpleaſes <hi>Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle de Guiſe;</hi> and the attempt I committed would not have been puniſhed ſo ſeverely in the Duke <hi>de Bellegard,</hi> as in me. You know it well enough, and cannot forget what <hi>Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle de Guiſe</hi> ſaid to you on that account, in the Garden at the Caſtle of <hi>Nemours:</hi> That di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:58051:75"/>was repeated to me, word by word; and I look on it as the ſource of all the rigor I have ſince met with. I will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpeak of it to any but you, and ſhall turn all my reſentment againſt my ſelf, and never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, but from death, any eaſe of my misfortunes: but, do me the favour to tell <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> I am perfectly informed of all my diſaſters; and that this which reduced me to the deſpair I am in, could not have been ſo great, had not others preceded it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>La Mothe</hi> had a particular eſteem for <hi>Givry,</hi> and was really concerned for the condition he appear'd in; ſhe did all ſhe could to give him ſome comfort. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times denying, and ſometimes qualifying what was ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Bellegard,</hi> ſo that it was
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:58051:76"/>not her fault he was not at better eaſe, but he was now become utterly incapable of any. The thought of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe</hi> ſlighting, angry, and prepoſſeſt in favor of a Rival, inſpir'd him with a thouſand deſperate reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions. He had much ado to force himſelf to ſpeak to Madam <hi>de Guiſe</hi> and Madam <hi>de Nemours,</hi> but was ſo far Maſter of Paſſion, that they obſerved not in him any alteration. Yet that moment of conſtraint did but render his fury after more violent: he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the King whom he found encamped before <hi>Laon,</hi> and gave him a thouſand thanks, from the Princeſſes for the complement he had vouchſafed to ſend them. They would have made their advantage of it, had their advice been taken, but the Duke of <hi>Mayenne</hi> was ſo accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:58051:76"/>to Command in Chief, he reſolved not to quit the Helm, but upon utmoſt extremity. The Town of <hi>Laon</hi> was taken, and the deſperate <hi>Givry</hi> ſought out ſo many occaſions to be killed, that he ſucceeded in his deſign, he was wounded upon a breach, and died of it three or four days after. He knew this ſervice would be hot, and being ſeriouſly reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to dye, writ to <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> before he went to the aſſault, a Letter, the Original whereof I have ſeen, and give you here the Copy <hi>verbatim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>YOu ſhall ſee, when you hear of my death, that I am a Man of my word, and that it was true I would live no longer than while I had the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of your favor, for finding
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:58051:77"/>you chang'd, I have recourſe to the ſole remedy I can apply in the caſe, going to dye unavoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dably. Since heaven loves you too well to ſave thoſe you would deſtroy, and muſt be at the expence of a Miracle to preſerve me from the danger I am running into: that death I ſeek, and know waits for me, makes me put an end to this Letter. Farewell then, fair Princeſs; and by the deſpair my reſpect to you hath redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced me to, Judge of the power of your ſlights, and whether I deſerved them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This Letter was not delivered to <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe;</hi> the man who had it to carry, having been taken priſoner by a Party of the Enemies, which is doubtleſs the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:58051:77"/>reaſon it came to our hands. But the Princeſs needed not a ſight of it to inform her what death the unfortunate <hi>Givry</hi> died. The King who was grieved at the heart for the accident, and ſcarce ſtirr'd from his Pillow thoſe two or three days <hi>Givry</hi> lived after he was wounded, drew from his own mouth the Confeſſion of his deſpair, and being returned to <hi>Paris</hi> complain'd grievouſly of it to <hi>Mademoiſelle de Guiſe.</hi> You have kill'd me <hi>Givry, Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle,</hi> ſays he to her, and have more weakned my Troops by that piece of your cruelty, than the Duke of <hi>Mayenne</hi> with all the ſtrength of his Arms. Had the favours I endeavor'd to do your Houſe made any impreſſion of acknowledgement upon you, you would have had more regard for a man ſo dear and ſo neceſſary to
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:58051:78"/>me, but you are ſufficiently pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd by the loſs you have of him. Nature produces not every day men of <hi>Givry</hi>'s character, and what beauty ſoever you may boaſt of, you will hardly ever ſee at your devotion a perſon ſo conſiderable as he was: <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle de Guiſe,</hi> who for ſome time paſt had not look'd with any favourable aſpect on <hi>Givry,</hi> made not ſo much account of the loſs of him. She did but ſmile at his Majeſty's reproaches, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to make him underſtand he was partly concerned in the exerciſe of that cruelty he bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m'd, her obliging Confeſſions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly wip'd away the thoughts of <hi>Givry</hi>'s death, out of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's mind. But nothing could have that power over the ſpirits of the too conſtant Madam <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giron,</hi> who fell ſick upon the
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:58051:78"/>News; and while <hi>Paris</hi> rung with joy for the abſolution of the King, and union of the Parties, this Lady dyed with the Name of <hi>Givry</hi> in her Mouth, <hi>Givry</hi> no leſs amiable than inconſtant and unfortunate.</p>
            <p>What Example more proper to make out the malignity of Love, and inſpire into us that horrour againſt it, it deſerves? <hi>Givry</hi> was the moſt accompliſht Perſon of his time, ſaw himſelf loaded with honour at ſix and twenty years of age, highly in favour with a great Monarch, his King; and in a fair way to obtain all the Dignities a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is capable of. An amorous deſpair deſtroy'd all his hopes, and robb'd the Kingdom of one of its Nobleſt Ornaments. The ſame Paſſion diſorder'd, and at laſt deſtroyed a Lady, whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:58051:79"/>and ſincerity deſerved bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fortune. The like end com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly make all thoſe, who abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely abandon themſelves to this fatal folly: if it makes but light impreſſion, it is an in exhauſtible ſourſe of perfideouſneſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude: if it be ſubmitted to in good earneſt, it leads into an exceſs of diſorder and deſpair.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:58051:79"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
